<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-black-bart</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014381/1883-11-15/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Last Monday evening the detectives of Wells,
Far.  Co., of whom J. B. Hume is chief, succeeded
in running down and capturing, after a long chase of
about six years, one of the most noted and darina*
stage robbers of the country, " Black Bart," as he is
generally known. His real name is said to be Cbas.
E. Bolton, although some doubt exists as to this
being his true patronymi *. Detective Hume was as-
sisted by Captain Stone, of the city police, and de-
tective Harry Morse.
CLUES THAT LED TO HIS CAPTURE.
Tbey found their man in the Webb House, on
Second street. His capture was effected in a pe-
culiar manner, and was in consequence of a clue left
by the highwayman at bis last operation, near Cop-
peropolis, on the morning of the 3d instant. As the
Sonora and Hilton stage was running over the
mountain road a man, whose face was concealed by
a flour sack that had beeu ripped open and cleansed,
jumped from behind the thicket skirting the roadway
and commanded a halt. He enforced bis bidding with
a presented revolver. No passengers were in the
stage at the time, aud the driver, M-Connell, was
compelled to get down from his seat, unharness the
horses and drive them behind the conveyance. The
robber then broke open the treasure-box of Wells,
Fargo & Co. and took therefrom 2*23 ounces of amal-
gam, valued at 81,100, which had come from the
Patterson mine, at Tuttletown ; three and a quarter
ounces of gold and *550 in gold and silver coin. As
McConnell drove the animals to the rear of the stage,
he noticed an Italian boy on the foothills a short
distance away, who was carrying a Henry rifle, with
which he had started out to bunt. He beckoned to
him, and the lad came. The robber had secured his
booty and was making off with it, when McCounell
seized the rifle from the boy's hands and fired at
the di spoiler. Black Bart, for it was undoubtedly
be, ran. McConnell pursued, and discharged three
more thots at bim. In running Black Bart lost his
hat, a little round Derby, and his handkerchief fell
out of his pocket. He also threw away a package
of papers that he had taken from the stage. These
were red with blood, and this fact induced McCon-
nell to think that one of his shots, at least, had
wounded the robber. The articles that Black Bart
had left behind were picked up later, wben a poe-e
of men from Copperopolis returned to the scene
after McConnell l.ad driven back to town.
A further clue, another piece of property, which
is presumed to belong to Black Bart, was fouud be-
hind some rocks near the spot wbere the stage was
stopped. This was the case of a pair of spyglasses,
which it is thought he used to descry the stage trom
afar and to note bow many were about it. On the
handkerchief was a laundry mark, which was the
means of securing his arrest.
A TELL-TALE MARK.
The articles were brought to this city. The mark
on the handkerchief was a private laundry mark,
and a search among the laundries of the city, Chi-
nese and otherwise, resulted. In a few .lays the
detectives located the users of the mark at a laun-
dry agency on Bush street, kepi by T. C. Ware.
From Mr. Ware it was found that the owner of the
handkerchief was C. E. Bolton, who was stopping
at the Webb House, No. 73 Second street, Room 40.
This person was immediately put under surveillance.
Hume notified a hunter near Stockton, who had
seen Bart, to hold himself in readiness to come
down aud identify th » man, the programme being to
make sure he was the proper person before making
the arrest. From all descriptions it was evident that
Black Bart and Bolton were the same.
A WARRANT FOR HIS ARREST.
Sheriff Thorn procured a warrant for his arrest on
a charge of stage robbery from the Superior Court
of Calaveras county, and armed with this document
he came to this city. It was found that the occu-
pant of Room 10, Webb House, was a well-known
man about town. He was thought to be a mining
man, having conveyed that impression in the society
of others by his conversation. His departures from
the city at various intervals were accounted for on
this supposition. He generally ate at the New York
Restaurant, on Kearny street, near Clay. He
was ever scrupulously neat and clean, and,
though he wore diamonds, was in do manner-dandy-
ish. His conversation was void of vulgarity ; he
never drank to excess, and ha.l no taste for tobacco.
His speech was ever civil and he treated all cordi-
ally. Boiton, it Be. Ms, was out of the city last
week, but returned Saturday. The Stockton hunter
saw him on the way from the train, and identified
him as Black Bart. On Monjay evening Captain
Stone, Captain Hume, Henry Morse and a fourth
party took a hack up town and were driven to No.
37 Second street, where they arrested Bolton with-
out much parleying. The same hack took the party
to the office of Captain Hume, where Bolton was ac-
cused of being Black Bart. <Be was shown that bis
captors had positive proof of his identity, Captain
Hume explaining that he had been tracking him for
six years, and bad is the last three years got a full
and minute description of the lone highwaymau ;
he rehearsed the story of the lost cuff and the silk
handkerchief, gave the history of the laundry mark
and suddenly cast the peculiar-lookicg hat at his
feet, as if to overwhelm him with evidence, but to
all this Mr. Bolton was impervious, an I said his real
nam,- was Spaulding; be smiled in a polite way, de-
nied everything, and passed the* night iv the tanks
at the City Prison.
TAKEN TO CALAVERAS,
He was registered in the small book under the
name of Spaulding, that he had last given. Yester-
day morning he took a ride on the cars to Stockton,
Detective Morse, Johnny Tbacker, of Wells, Fargo
& Co a force, and Captain stone, of the regular
police force, accompanying him. At Stockton his
photograph was taken. From thfnce ho resumed
his journey to San Andreas, Calaveras county,
where he was given quarters in the jail, and where
he will bo t ried. On his person when arrested was
found film in gold and $10 in silver The latter
sum he was allowed to retain. The Derby hat fitted
him so accurately that he said he was almost
tempted to buy it. In his room nothing of pecuni-
ary value was found, but an old suit of clothes,
identified as those worn by him when he robbed the
Sonora and Milton stage, was pickel up. These hi
had discarded for newer garments, which be bought
in Sacramento last week, aud which he had on
when arrested.
BLACK HARTS CAREER.
Block Bart is a native of Jefferson county, New
York, and 40 years of age. His first appearance in
California was made on the 3d day of August, 1577.
He then introcuced himself to the express company
by stepping out on the road in front of the stage,
then winding its wav from Fort Ross to Russian
river, and, w.th a double-barrelea shotgun, de-
manding that the treasure-box and mail hags be
thrown to him. The box, followed quickly by the
mail bugs, slid from the drivers hands in a twink-
ling ; the driver, at a sign from the man, whipped
up his team and disappeared in the dust of the
road, leaving the stranger to rifle the box of about
S3OO in coin, a check for $305 62 drawn on the
Grangers Hank In this city in favor of Fisk Bros.,
and relieve any letters which contained coin of their
contents. About one year after the above robbery,
July 85, 1870, the stage from yuincy to Oroville
was stopped by one man, and Wells, Fargo & ( o.s
box robbed of $379 in coin, one diamond ring (said
to be worth $200), one silver watch valued at 825.
The mail was alio robbed. In the box, when fbtind
next day, was the following :
Here I lay me down to sleep
To wait the coming morrow.
Perhaps success, perhaps defeat,
And everlasting sorrow.
Yet come whit will. Ill try it on,
My condition caut be worse,
And if theres money in that box
Tis money in mv purse.
BLACK BART, the P o 8.
REWARDS FOR HIS CAPTDBE.
The Governor offered $300 reward for his arrest
an.l conviction ; Wells, Fargo & Co. added $300 to it
and the prstal authorities $200 more, making a total
of (800. This reward was repeated with every fresh
roboery, until now, if his captors can convict lUm of
committing all the robberies, which he undoubtedly
did commit— twenty-thre« at least they will be en-
titled to an aggr.-ca*.- of $18,400 Following are
some of tbe operations in which, it is believed. Black
Bart was the principal :
About 8 o clock a. v. of July 30, 1878, the down
state from Laporte to Oroville wis robbed by one
man, who took from the expresa-box a rackage
gold specimens valued at 850, and a silver watch,
No. 710 999, P. 8. Bartlett, maker. The mail was
also robbed.
On the 2.1 of October, 1878, the stag.- from Cahto
to I kiali, Mendocino county, was stopped by one
man an.l the express box a...l mail robbed.
On the following day, October 3, 1878, the stage
from Covelo to L kiah was stopped by one man and
the express box and mail robbed. After the last
robbery the Sheriff and officers of Mendocino county
traced the robber in the direction of Colusa, via
Bartlett Springs. The la-t heard of him was within
eight miles of the town of Williams, Colusa county.
On the lbt day ot September, 1880, the stage from
Wcarerviile to Shasta was stopped by one man, and
the express box and mail robbed. On the following
day the robber came to a house on Eagle creek,
Shasta county, procured breakfast and a luncheon
to carry with him, and upou leaving started toward
Tehama county.
On October 8, ISSI, the stage from Yreka to Red-
■ iii f win stop;. by one nnn and : .- express box
and mail robbed.
On the Itth of Octobsr, 1881. the stage from A!tu-
raa to Redding was stopped by one man and the
express box and mail robbed. The robber was
traced down the valley, on the east side of the Sac-
ramento river, within three miles of Oroai le, Butte
county, stopping at farm-house, on the way to pro-
cure food.
On December 15, 1*81, the stage from Downieville
to Mir.- » :.s stopped by one man, and the ex-
press box and mail rob led.
On .ii. .- 27, 1831, the stage from San Juan to
Smartsville was stopp-.-d t.y one man, and the ex-
press box and mall robbed.
On January 2 , 18»z. the stage from I kiah to
!< -. - r i.tie was stopped by one man, and the express
box and mail robbed. After this robbery It Is be-
lieved the robber went toward Clear Lake, crossed
at the Narrows appetite Kelseyvllle, and passed
down via Bartlett Springs toward Colusa.
On July 1., 188, the stage from Laporte to Oro-
ville was stopped by one man. George Hac «ett,
Wells, Fargo & Co. a meesenger. was on the stage,
and fired two shots at the robber without effect.
The robber escaped to the brush and fled, going
south. He was seen on the following day near
C*mptonvi!le, V üba county.
i.. September 17, 1871, the stage from Yreka to
Redding was Slopped by one Bin, and the express
box and mail robbed.
On the 2tth ot November, 1882, the stage from
Lakeport to Cloverdaie was stopped by one man,
and tbe express box and mail robbed The robber
went east md north, toward Lower Lake.
All Of the above have been attributed to Black
Hart on account of tbe similarity in the mr de of
operation, and by the Invariable doggerel left be-
hind.
Early in the spring of the current year he ap-
parently went  on the road again, for on April
12th the stage running between Lakeport and
Cloverdaie was stopped ny one man.
On June 23d la«t,_*he stage from Jackson to lone
(Sty was robbed by a single person.
DESCRIPTION OF BLACK BART.
Black Bart Is an American, about 50 years of age,
five feet nine Inches in bight, weighs about one
hundred anil fifty-five pounds, high forehead, promi-
nent cbtek bones, lower part face long and thiß,
light gray eyes, deep set heavy eyebrows, gray
hair and mustache.! and long soft hands. He is a
teetotaler In the matter of liquor and tobacco, but
Is a great lover of c ffee. He is also very fond of
reading, and devours all sorts of literature ; Every
lino of his poetry Is written la a different hand, the
style ranging from an attempt to imitate the labori-
ous work of a school-be y to a handsome, dashing
business hand, betokening great experience with a
pen.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014381/1883-11-17/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Black Bart" Pleads Cnllty— Craa*
Valley Outrage Case- Vessel la Flames—
Chlrlcahuas Surrendering— Banal] Fire
at Ogden— Advices from Oregon— The
Colton Case— Man Killed la a Well-
Arizona Items— Etc.
[Sr—l—i DISI-ATaHKS TO THI KICOBD-UMOJS.]
I CALIFORNIA.
.
The Supposed "Black Bart" Pleads
•.■llly.
San Andreas, November 16th.— Black
Bart was examined before Justice P. H. Kean
to-day. He pleaded guilty to the charge of
highway robbery committed near Copperopo
lis, in this county, on November 3, 1883. He
was held to appear before the Superior Court.
He, with detectives Morse, Stone and Sheriff
Thorn, went to the place where the treasure
was hid in the stamp of a tree near the scene
of the robbery, and recovered all the treasure
stolen, which was given to detective Morse
for shipment to Welle. Fargo & Co. at San
Francisco. Sheriff Thorn, in testifying be
fore Justice P. H. Kean, stated that tbe
prisoner bad confessed to him that he had
committed the robbery, and then told where
he had buried the treasure. The prisoner
carries an indifferent air, and has been via
ited whilst in jail by many people. He has
nat confeised to any other robbery, and has
given his name as C. E. Burton, and says he
is not Black Bart. An information will be
filed against him to-morrow morning, and he
will probably plead guilty at once, asd be
speedily sentenced by the Superior Court.
About "Black Bart.**
San Francisco, November 16th.— Captain
Curtin, of the Morse Agency, tc-day re
ceived a letter from Harry Morse at Copper
opolis, saying that he would not be down to
the city for some time, as he wi-hed to de
vote several more daya to listening to Black
Bart's stories and in tracing up possible clues
to other concealed mail matter and treasure.
No dispatches of importance were received
by Wells, Fargo — Co. to-day. A large num
ber of photographs of Black Bart have been
issued, and are in great demand in this city
and in the districts where he bas been operat
ing. Many persons about the Stock Ex
change and " pauper alley " affirm that they
have frequently seen the notorious highway
man in the role of a quiet stock speculator.
Ship on Fire.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87090966/1884-01-15/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The following details relating to the early
life of "Black Bart," the highwayman poet,
arc taken from a letter of an acquaintance to
a relative in this city. It Is believed that they
will prove of Interest, and it is hoped that the
moral for his early penchant for athletics will
not be lost on the juvenile portion of the
community. The writer says: "Charles E,
Bawles was bora In England. His father,
John Bowles, emigrated to this country in
1820 or 1S30, Charles being about 2 years
old, and settled in the town of Alexandria,
Jefferson county, New York, where he be
came a lariner and accumulated some proper
ty He raised a family of 10 children three
daughters and seven sens, Charles being next
to the youngest son and lived to the ripe old
age of 84 years, honored and respected by all
his neighbors and acquaintances, and died In
aepicmoer, 1072. sua wue oiea uuricg in
same month, at the aee of 80 years,
"Charley, as we usually called him. re
ceived a common school education, and when
trown up became belter known than any
other young man in this section on account of
excelling in amieuc sports, ana was prooaoiy
lor nis wcigni tne oesi couar-ano-eiuow
wrestler In Jelfersoa county. He was a young
man of excellent habits and greatly esteemed
and respected by all who knew mm.
" In 1841 he. with bis brother David, went
West, and in 1850 started across the plains fur
California, and after about four months of
ereat hardships arrived there and engaged in
miniag with moderate success. In the fall of
1550, ascertaining that your uncle James and
I were working on the north fork of the
American river, they came lo our cabin on
Union bar and finally decided to remain with
us. which they did, and we all worked to
gelker until the fall of 1851, when be started
lor home, arriving there in January. lSc.2.
"After remaioing with his' father about
three months Charley again started lor (.an
forala. accompanied by his boyhood com
panions. David and Robert were both taken
sick on the passsge out, and David died in
Saa Francisco and Robert lived but a short
time aficr arriving in ike.mines, making a sad
ending to all their hopes of acquiring wealth
and then returning home to spead their re
maining years In the quiet enjoyment of home
me.
"After a few years he returned home agaii
staying with his father only a short time, lien
going to the State of Illinois, where he was
married, and within a year or two he returned
with his wife to work bis father's farm; but
farming not being to bis taste, he ijn'n went
west and returned and moved Ms i-jilly to
Illinois, where he resided when the rebellion
broke out.
"I understand that he enlisted as a private
soldier, but was soon promoted on account el
galant service, always being found at the front
wnen tuere was any iiguiiog to ne uone,
served faithfully until the end af the '
when he was honorably discharged. He was
wounded several times, aad if accounts are
true about his disabilities, he should be draw
log a pension. </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1884-04-05/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A POET HIGHWATHllfi
The Slnriilar Hahlu of Ihr Terror o*
the West.
how black part's milo voice became familiar
TO TRAVELERS? HK TRIES THE <X?NKOLATORT
power OF POETRT?some SPECIMEN s OF HIS
RHYME?he FINALLY FALLS INTO THE CLUTCHES
OP THE LAW.
Among the papers that recently passed
through the hands of the Treasury officials was
an account amountingto ? 200 paid toone Harry
Morse, of San Francisco, for services rendered
the government in tlie arrest of Black Hart,
the Po 8, a name as familiar to stage-drivers on
the Pacific slope as was that of Claude Duval
to those in Kngland In days of old. Attracted
by the singularity of the name. an interrogation
point of The Star inquired into the facts
ot the case.
Four years ngo a stage running not ween a
mining town in California and a raiiroad station
was stopped by an individual concealed in
the bushes bordering the road. Plainly to be
seen amidst the foliage was the muzzle of a
double-barreled shotgun: only this and nothing .
more: yet upon the simple requestor the unknown.
spoken in a mild voice, the driver threw i
the mail bags into the road and half a dozen ;
stalwart male passengers stood in a line with
their hands above their heads, while the driver j
again accommodated the sottly-spoken stranger
by turning inside out the pockets of the unfortunate
passengers, depositing their contents
upon the mail bags. The t-tage w as then allowed
to proceed, and it made excellent time to
the nearest station, where reinforcements were ;
secured, and the party returned to the scene ot
the outrage with the laudable intention of;
decorating the highest branch of the highest
tree in the vicinity with the person of the highwayman.
The country was scoured for two
days, but the only trace left by the gentleman
whose company was in sufh urgent request
were the following lines, evidently written in a
disguised hand, with the exception of the signature:
the poetry of the road.
Now T lay nie down to sleep
Not earing for t he morrow.
Perhaps good luck, perhaps defeat
And jail fare, to my sorrow.
Then come what will, I ll try my luck,
I m sure It can t be worse,
For if there s money In that pouch,
It s money in my purse.
Black Bart, the Po 8.
This unique production was found scrawled
upon a torn newspaper wrapper lying upon one
ot the rifled mail baas. That was the first time
the name of Black Bart was heard, but it was
not the last, for one stage line after another in
rapid succession paid heavy tribute to him.
Wells, Fargo A Co. were large losers, and after
trying guards without avail offered *800 reward
for the capture of the highwayman. The state
officials bestirred themselves, and eventhe U.S.
government awakening to the frequent conplaints
of losses of valuable malls, put in motion
its ponderous machinery and offered a reward
of *200 in addition to the $800 offered by
Wells, Fargo & Co. The extent to which private
enterprise was stimulated thereby may be
judged by tne story of l?an Shealy, a driver of a
stage running out of Copperapolls. Said Dan
Jo one of the detectives:
1 got a notion in my head that I d like to
earn that pile, but I dfdu t quite see my way
clear. Black Bart had been heard from about a
week back of the day I m talking about in a
neat little affair over to the westward of Copperopolis.
aud that darned mean piece of poetry
he hitched onto the mail-bag (like kicking a
man when he s down) kinder made me think
he was going over on the Yuba route next. I d
almost fixed it up to take a week off. go over
there and lay for him. Was going to hang on
behind the stage, you see. and have a try at
him under the wheels if I played in luck. Old
Yankee Daniels, at Copperopolis. told me I was
a darned fool, and that the Po 8 would be long
my way soon enough, but I wasn t discouraged,
aud keyt thinking it over. Next trip I d gotten
about hve miles out of old Cop. when
homeuody sl'no ol't halt,'
and I heard two sharp ciicks. Seemed as if the
critters knew what's the proper thing for they
Stopped as quick as if they'd struck a stable.
Then somebody in the bushes axed me pleasantlike
to hold my hat on with both hands for some
buck-shot might blow it off. along with some
hair and skull. If I didn't. I alius was reasonable
and I dropped that express chest with
rklOO of Welle. Fargo'scoln and drove off just
like 'twas the regular thing. When the posse
got back there they found an old axe that he'd
used to bust the box, and on the cover he'd
etuck this yer:
Once I tolled for gold in ditches
Jiow witn ease I amass riches,
Dahlel: now I'm on this lay,
I'll come again another day.
Well, sir, that riled me. There I'd been laving
off to catch my man and he'd carried me
Into camp like a iamb, and now he'd the cheek
to tell me he's going to come It over me again.
I put a month's wages in a gun, tilled her full
of slugs and got ready for a fracas. Old Yank
offered to buy my lite' insurance policy; the old
cuss. I'd taken to carrying my arsenal 'crow
my knees when I struck the lonesome places.
Went along like that tor 'bout two weeks.
There's a pretty steep hill about two miles out
of town and the critters are 'bout winded when
they strike the level above. One Friday I'd a
heavy load, mall, express and passengera, including
three gals, and I let the cattle crawl up
the hill. I'd alius been s'plclous of that place
and I'd dropped the lines onto the foot-board
and taken up my shooting iron half 'spectlng
my man. Pilgrim, he was right there. Just as
we struck the crest something flew out'en the
bush like a catamount, lit under tho neck
of the nigh leader, and 'fore I could say Jack
Robinson I was looking into a couple o' holes
In a chunk of Iron. Stop? Yas; I stopped.
He'd the drop on me agin. Couldn't blaze away
'thout killing the lead horse, and wouldn't have
fazed the cuss, for I couldn't see nothing 'sides
one eye. He was dressed iu a long linen duster
and had a Hour bag over his head. Sed he'd
taken a fancy to my gun that trip, and
I let him have it. But darned If he didn't shove
a fifty onto the box to pay me when he'd gotten
through the matinee. He never would bother |
the women folks, but was mighty polite to them.
The boys got onto that racket, and I've known
a single poor Irish lass going over my route to
carry the nuggets ot half a dozen miners. Yes;
I rememlier the poetry he left that time. It
was like this:
Daniel, It grieves me to say it,
Next I lme you attempt to play It,
Buy an overcoat of pine,
And I'll send the corpse In time.
I quit the line after that; didn't think it was
healthy."
nE ELUDES CAPTURE.
The records show that the government pet
forth every effort, through Its trained iupectors,
to capture the audacious mail depredator.
Wells, Fargo & Co., through their
agents, kept the local authorities up to their
work, while the standing rewards Incited individual
enterprise. But the robberies continued,
and the tantalizing rhymes left at the scene of
each new exploit showed that the "Po 8" was
aware of the efforts that had been made to
secure his capture. Nobody had ever seen his
lace, and the insjieotors' reports stated that all
evidence was to the effect that he never slept
over night within fifteen or twenty miles of the
scene ot his adventure.
Finally Detective Morse took up the trail, and
through* inductive reasoning he placed the man
he sought in San Francisco.
"What does Black Bart do with the proceeds
of his robberies," mentally inquired Morse, and
the answer was that he sjtent it, and spent it in
San Francisco, too. So the detective resigned
to others the task of following Black Bart all
over the state, while he sought him in the slums
ot San Francisco. He searched for weeks without
success, until onedav when his attention was
attracted by a peculiar ruby in the window of a
jewelry store. It exactly fitted the description
of a Jewel taken by Black Baft from a wealthy
drover some months before. The gentleman
who left the ruby, said the jeweler, had often
sold to him other jewels.
CACGHT AT LAST.
Following up this clue, the detective shadowed
the shop and soon had the gentleman under
arrest. It was none other than Black Bart,
as it afterwards appeared, although he
stoutly denied his Identity. He was ta
man of about fifty years of age, neatly
dressed, and with a soft, pleasant voice, which
was rarely heard. He was a native of New
York, hailed from Calaveras county, and had
been an unsuccessful miner. His habits were
exemplary; he did not swear, nor did he use tobacco
or drink liquor. During his trial he maintained
an air ot injured innocence that so impressed
the court that it was only through herculeau
efforts that the prosecution was able to
have him sentenced to six years servitude in
states prison for robbing the Copperapolls stage.
It was the only stage robbery with which he
could be connected, because in the other cases
his Identity had been completely concealed by
his disguises. His victims, however, the passengers
in the Stage coaches, seldom got more
than a glimpse of him, as he usually required
the driver to collect his tolls while he remained
conce aled by the roadside.
Alter his conviction the "Po 8" talked more
freely," and from a confession made to an inspector
of the Post Office department It appears
that he had committed twenty-nine highway
robberies within two years. In transmitting a
copy of the confession the inspector in his endorsement
sajs that it Is lair to assume that the
"Po 8" had perpetrated many other similar
crimes not enumerated in his list. because It in
an almost invariable trait of criminals to confers
only to minor crimes in the t-flort to divert attention
from the greater violations of law. The
endorsement also reads that although the prisoner
has confessed these crimes, he has purposely
tailed to supply certain links in the chain of
testimony, so that it is not probable that he
could be convicted ot them In court, although
there can be no moral doubt of his guilt.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn99021999/1888-01-03/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>"BLACK BART , " THE ROBBER ,
The Here of Twonty-Throo Stage
ltobborloa Released Froni Prison.
HIS MANY ADVENTURES.
A. Bandt Who had no 'ico Escopt a
for Oilier ' '
Liking I'copie's
Money-How ho Evaded Ar.
rest.
"Black Burt , time Poe-B , " time most
fanmoims stage robber on the commat , viio
coimiuiiittcml twommty-threo robberies dum-
lug sixyemmrs , was released fromu Saum
Quen timi , Califormmla , emi Now
Year's day. lb promises to turn over mm
new leaf timid lead an honest life , nuid lim
view of this resoivo a brief history his
career will be found more than usually
interesting , as time histories of stage
robbers go. It Is told be a San Frau-
cisco corrospomidunt of the Globe-Demo-
crat , as follows :
Black Dart Is time most celebrated of
nil the skillful hmigitwaymaum , or road
agents , as they are called , who hare
Ilourisimed emi time Pacific coast sluice the
early days of time gold rush. For six
years ho wits the togror of Wells , Fargo
& Co.'s express agommts. Ho soemned to
be ubiquitous. Ho first levied on mm
small concim in time Sierras , timid the mmoxt
hoard of him would be in time lonely Sis-
kiyotm mountains , on the old trail Into
Oregon. He was always alone , and imo
noverfailed to do his work iii system-
title amid gentlemanly fashion. If
there was nimy doubt in time
driver's mind of the identity
of time lomme highwayman , tItle
doubt svmis always dispelled when time
detectives arrived eu time eccimo of the
robbery. Attached to the rifled cx-
liCn' box would always be fommnd sonme
bit of 1)miper , with a low lines of dog-
goral P0ettY. signed , "Black Bart , time
Pee 8. " The express company has in
its oinmloy some of the most skillful detectives -
tectives in time country , yet these men
were always bailled by "Black Dart. "
Up to time time of his capture they did
not even know his minnie or any of his
haunts. The cimief cause of this mystery -
tory was that Dart was a pimenomnonal
crinmimial mviio never had any commfldaimts
. -lievom. drank liquor nor had ammy rein-
tions with women. In this way amost of
time sources of information upon which
time police rely were cut off. Bart ,
wheim not on the road , was known In this
cityand Sacrainommto as Charles B. Benton -
ton , or Dalton , and Charles Barlow. He
was supposed to be a mining man who
made frequmont trips Into time interior to
looic after his proporties. These trips ,
it is needless to say , were always
marked bya "clean-up , " but this was
made at time express company's expense ,
amid time only tools that time ingenious
mnincr used was a shotgun , to pursuado
ammy refractory stage-coach driver , and
Ii crowbar or axe to breaic open the cx-
press cohmmpany's box.
Tflhi ROAD AGENT'S METUODS.
Black Bart was finally captured In
November , 1883 , but this occurred only
after ho had pursued his lucrative call-
lug for six years. A brief sketch of'his
career and of his methods may not be
without Interest. His first ltpptmflrttllCO
in California. was on August 8 , 1877 ,
when he halted the regular snail stage
from Fort Ross to the Russian river.
The road at this point is along a high
bluff , amid , on time day mnommtioned , as the
stage swung around a sharp curve , the
leaders wore halted by a scarecrow
figure iii the middle of time road with a
doublobarrelod shotgumm In his hand.
Thu imike-up of the road agent was
unique. He had jute wimeatbags on the
lower part of his legs ; his body was clad
ill an old iimmomm duster amid his head and
face wore covered with a white flour-
sack , through which gleamimed the bright
black eyes of the robber. On his head
imo imad a cap which bore a striking ro-
somnbianco to the comical hat of the
circus clown.
Ins FIRST IIOBTIERY.
Before the astonished driver could
fairly take in this strange apparation Ito
was asked in politotones , "l'iease throw
omit time box mmimd mail-bags. " As time
fun was traimied cmi him hum lost imo time
mm ) oboyimmg. Thmoim time figure mmiinbiy
leaped to the side of the road and ordered -
dered him to drive on. No attempt was
made to rob any passengers in the
couch.
Whoim flue stmmge reached the next
statiomm time sheriff started out , but ho
foumid ommiy time thlalidmmted treasure box ,
time rifled mail-bngsaimd nut old ax. Frommm
time bOX the road agent had secured $300
In coin , a check on a San Francisco
bmtiik for $305.52. On time back of a way
bill of the comnpany twats scribbled time
legend which was soon to be so well
kmmown , "Black Dart , the Poo-8. " Time
humorous signature of time highwayman
caused much amuscmemmt througimout
the state , but time cpress
officers timought lie was a crank , and
they bad heard the last of him.
TWENTY-TIIIIEE SUCCESSFUL HAULS.
Rewards amouuitimig to $800 in all wore
offered for the eapttmre of time stage rob' .
1)Cr , iUt not a clew wits gained by imumy
of time smnmihl army of detectives that
worked on the ease. Time detectives had
only fairly given U time imumit when another -
other stage robbery by a lone lmighway-
man was reported Ill Moimdocino coummty
mind among the debris of mail bags and
express ioxes wore some execrable vom'-
see , signed by "Black Burt. " Again
rewards were offered , timid again unavailing -
availing search was mmmdc. Durimmg the
mmoxt five years Wells Fargo & Co.'s express -
press boxes were robbed by this practical -
tical hmighwaymnamm about four times a
year. He mmcvur tackled mm stage that
hUtch a shotgumi muessemiger : lie mmever die-
turbed a mussemmger , but was mmotorious
for his 1)OiitefleSS to womnon 0mm board ,
whom he assured timat no imarm would
iOfhtll them ; yet ho nlway got away
with a good swag , his clean-ups rangimig
from $300 to $3,000. Ho seemed to have
U litrtiality for gold dust and amalgam
but Ito also appeared to have means o ?
kmiowing viicn heavy coin shmijmncmmts
wore made. In timis way. durimmg the
six years that lie worked so regularly ,
ho commid not Intro averaged less timamm
$6X)0 ( ) a year , wimicim emummo out of time
imocicots of time express company and out
of Ummele excimequers.
A FORTUNE OFFERED IN REWAIITIS.
Aitimougim ime always wore a sack ever
his imead , it was eomnetimne carelessly
adjusted , ammd the drivers of stages were
notified to take special pniums to get a
deseriptiomi Of imihfl. In this waytimc detectives -
toctives flumully hind a good tlcscriptioa.
They knew Imo was about fifty , aim Amnem-
icamm , with lomig gray imnir , timimm lace ,
(1001)-Set gray eyes and pronmimiont teeth ;
timuit ho was a teetolor and fond of read-
lug ; that he always wrote imis doggerel
1mm a different imnmmd , iut mit timmmes ho-
trayed gmtmat prficitiney with time pen.
Yet this imotograph of time mnyeteriotms
crimInal did imot seem to aid them at till
1mm time semircim for him. The rewards i
November , iSS3 , iuul reacimed the hand-
50010 sum of $18,400. Every mobbevy
was committed tim JmeeiSelY time same
mvay. The rmuil bags iveme always. cut
jtm.t iieiow time lock iii time form of a let-
tet' T , and the ax with which time cx-
- - - - - - _ .
' - - - ' - - - - - -
press'box wn broken opeim was bit on
tlhgrountl ,
TIAIIT'S LA5i flommr.itY. .
Perhaps ho would still be levyIng ohm
time stages In title stab if it bud tint
been for a bit of caroicesmiess on time
imiorning of Noveambor 8 , 1883 , whmemi lie
robbed the stuigo betwcum Milton amid
Sommormi , iii Tuohmumno eouumty , about
three tidIes front Coppeiopol1s , cmi time
old mail road front time Yosenilto. it
wna his twemity-timird sthgo i'obbeiy , amid
lie imad locoumc so expert that Ime 1150(1 a.
powerfimi pair of field glasses to detect
wimetimor timmy nrmiiod mnesseumger was out
the stage. 0mm timis dnv McConnell , the
tiriver , imunl allowed a boy of time imeigh-
1orimood , vlmo imiul It guim , to ride with
imliii , but time lad got dowmm just before
time stmmgo mvas stopped and lund mm goume
imito time woods to hunt.Vimetm hart
imalteti time stage Imo mmmdceml mtcCommiiell
what had bocoummo of time mnnn with time
guilt. Time drivem told hmimn time trutiiwimetm
Dart orderemi imiumi to throw tiown time
box and to unlmlteh his iRrses , Thou
Burt vent through time box like an old
imitmid , getting * 4,400 of amnigmunated
gold , 21 ounces of goiti iltist , and $5T,0 imm
coin uickmiges. lie gathered timeso up
mum ins arnie , said "good-bye" to time
driver , mmnti was scarcely oume lmnmmdrod
yards away whoum time boy with time rifle
nPPoarod. Mr. McConnell snatched the
rifle and fired four shinto mit time retreat-
immg robber , but time thick bushes pro-
vomited him front taking gooin alum ,
A 1ECULIAIi CLnW.
Whion the detectives explored the
scommo a tow imonis biter they found time
romnmmnnts of Bam't's eiitnji fire amid imoar it
a slouch lint , a silk imnmmdkercimiof , timid a
liumcmi cuff ms'ltim blood stain oum It.Vimmmt
delighted timeimi , imowevorammd furnislmed
the first real clew timey html evem' gaimmed.
was a laundry ninth on time cuff. IL was
time mnmirk used by ammo of time city stenum
lauimdries , and time detectives at once
scoured Sami Fraimeisco for tim ummmmui mvimo
hind handled this mark. Timer fouumd
hitmi to be a htmutidmy ngotmt 1mm this city
aumd lie ideumtifled time cuff mis belommglzmg
to C. E. Bolton , a maui who hind clothing
awaiting him at time otiice. His tioscrip-
tioum of Iloltoum tallied pretty closely with
time hippemtrttimeo of Dart. So time iletec-
tires laid fom' the appcaraimco of the
stage robber. Ho returimed in exactly a
wcok frohn the ditto of time roTbcry ammu
was arrested mis ito calledfor his clothes.
lie professed great iumdigmmation at imie
amrost , but a search of his i'oomim led to
time discovom'y of his real name amid to
the fmndiuig of a number of article of
clothing vithm the idemmtical nmnrk ott iimo
culT. His real umaummo was Charles B.
Belles , its it was found In a family bible
amid in a discharge trout time regular
nrtny , in which lie served durimig time
war.
EnCOVEItY OF THU AMALGAM.
Dart was takemi . to Stockton , whore
he was picked out of a. crowd of 200
mnon , by a hunter who saw him a few
itours after time robbery. Title idemmti-
fieation rather staggered Bart , hut lie
still laughed' at time officers , ummtil timmit
mmight , wimen Detectives Thormm ammd
Stone laid before Imim all time evidences
they hind secured.
"Cmiii you prove all that ? " quietly
asked time prisoner.
"I can , " returned Thorn.
"All right , " said Dart , "let's travel. "
Witimouta word Thorn wommt out , ordered -
dorod a team and at 1 o'clock in time
morning tiireo officers amid Dart started
for time scene of time roibcry. Bart
acted as it guide , andtooic tlmcm to mm imol-
low buckeye , not far from time road ,
ivimore the plunder was concealed. Hero
everything was found except the coin ,
which Bart declared ho had sFeult. Ho
was bromight to title city and locked tip.
Ho pleaded guilty to this one robbery ,
but strenuously denied timat ho was the
famous stage robber Ho made an up-
peal to time court , declaring timat it was
only urgent hiecessity tiimit drove him
to the crime , and time result was he received -
ceived oimly six years in San Qucmmtin.
He was sentenced November 17 , 1883 ,
just a fortumigimt after his robbory.
IN 1118 PItIVATIl CHARACTER.
When the aliases umider whicit lie was
wider wimieli ho was known hero ivero
published , mm large number of people
recogmmized time stage robber as a man
wimom they had known for five years.
His landlady had been acquainted with
him all this time. Ho always paid
promptly. Ho boarded at a i'ostaurant
whore lie was wont to entertain his
fricumds with army reminiscenses. He
elaimned to have been captaimm In an
Oimio regiment , and ho was a good story-
teller. More than a dozen policemen
knew imim , timid imad frequently talked
witim imim whim ) a small fortune was
awaiting the inaui wimo simould arrest
and identify imimn as Black Bart. Time
story appealed to the popular inimigilma-
tiomi , amid created agreateensation here.
1115 1'RISON RIFE.
\Vheim Dart svmms finally transferred to
Sami Quentin , lie mmmdc no secret ok his
idommtity , but he refused to talk or imis
irovious eX1)lOits. lie declared that ho
imnl ( robbed his last stage , amid that
when he got out lie would lend utim imoum-
est life. lie imuts been a model prisoner ,
givimmg no trouble to time ollicers. Ho
has worked during time greater part. of
his imprisonment in the drug depart-
memmt of time prison , amid lie has no-
come tin oxpem't chemist. Officers who
have imad lomig experioumce with crimni-
nmile are doubtful of the imigitwayinaum's
relemitlimicO , but lie is sowoil known mmcmv
imm California tinit It would be useless
for him toattempt to operate as a road
zmgeimt anywhere on the coast. Wimetimer
ito retires from time road or not , lie still
retnaiums one of time pimehiolneumal crimE-
nals of time age-mm maim who pursued a
busimmoss that requires un paralied nerve
amid ' 'sand , " and who miovor simowod imny
traces of feaf iii thoworet prcdicammiommt</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn90059522/1888-07-01/ed-1/seq-14/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The recent
appearance of "Black Bart" in the San
Joaquin valley has set California to
wondering if this, at one time most dar
ing and eccentric robber and highway
man, contemplates resuming the busi
ness that he made so successful ten
years ago.
Then his name was enough to strike
terror to the hearts of unprotected
females who were obliged to go by
stage coach from coast points to inland
towns, and when it fell on the ears of
strong men, they instinctively clutched
their pocketbooks and looked for some
avenue of escape.
Ten years ago "Black Bart" held up
stage coaches on the roads of Northern
and Central California, and put the
Wells-Fargo Express company to maeh
expense to protect their property from
him. Ten years ago he became too
daring, and one night while under the
Influence of liquor he reeled through the
streets of Bedding shooting his revolvers
at the doorways and windows, and sub
sequently landed in the penitentiary at
San Quinten to serve a term of ten
years which expired about two months
ago.
In face and figure "Black Bart" was a
handsome man. He was of Mexican
parentage, and possessed the tall,
straight figure of that race. He let his
plossy hair grow long and it fell like a
silken veil over his shoulders. His dark
and perfect features were rendered
norm.v ath:a.
by a black mustache that curved grace
fully across his upper lip.
More than this is not known of
"Bart's" early life. About it he has al
ways kept his lips sealed. Associates
he never had. He always "played a
lone hand"' and made a confident of no
one.
In all his career as a highwayman he
was never known to kill a person,
though his nefarious business was car
ried on at the point of a revolver or rifle,
and his body bears many scars made by
bullets from the guns of watchful
guards when he became too venture
some. His hobby was to rifle mail
sacks, and he never was in better spirits
than when he bad held up a mail coach,
relieved the driver and passengers of
their arms, money and jewelry, and,
With his rifle within easy reach, sat
down near his helpless victims
and keeping one eye on them ripped
open love letters, business notes, regis
tered letters, read the contents or a
part of them to his listeners and tucked
them hack into the mail pouch through
a rent in Ihe side, made by his knife,
a jumbled mass.
One of the eccentricities of this
strange robber was to write a piece of
poetry whenevever he robbed the mail
and shove it into the pouch when be
had finished sorting out the valuable
part of its contents. To these notes in
rhyme he would always sign the norn
de plume "Black Bart" and as this he
came to be known among men. In the
office of the warden at the San Quinten
penitentiary there are two bits of
"Bart's" poetry found in mail pouches
that he rifled in '00. They were written
with a lead pencil, in a legible hand,
which indicates that the man had from
some source gathered
SOME fi;agme_ts
of an education. One of the poems,
a quatrain, indicates his disgust at the
poor haul he made, in the following
words:
I'm sorry I spent my time,
Hipping up this mail.
I didn't lind money enough,
To buy a feeding for a quail.
—Black Bart. .
Another, a distich, tells of a profit
able haul and the writer's satisfaction,
It runs thus:
Such haul? as this are very rare;
' They soon would make mo a millionaire.
—Black Bart.
Two peculiarities of the man were his
tender heartedness and his courtesy to
ladies. If he found money in a letter
that had been sent by anyone to a
relative anil by the tone of the letter he
•was satisfied that the person to whom it
was addressed was in needy circum
stances, he would Inclose the money
in the torn envelope and handing it to
the driver, make film promise to have it
re-addressed when he reached town.
He was extremely polite to ladies and
was never known to take their money
or jewelry, but if he found fire-arms
concealed about them, he never hes
itated in appropriating them.
"Bart" once held up flic coach running
between Marysville, Cal., and Carson
City, Nev. There was a young man
among the passengers, who had come
out from the East and gone into the
mountains for the benefit of his health.
His visit had only temporarily bene- i
fitted him and he was on his way
home in the last stages of consumption.
I
We had but little over a hundred dol
lars, and whin "Bart" took it from his
Inside pocket he asked him where he
was going.
"Home, to Massachusetts," replied
the young man.
"is this all the money you've got?"
Inquired "Bart."
"Every cent, so help me God," tremu
lously replied the young man, naturally
thinking the highwayman suspected
him of having more '■ money : concealed
about his person.  ,:: . _>-.. --,. -._ :•• ...
"Bart" unbuckled a belt from around
his waist and counting out 1500 in gold,
handed it to the astonished consumptive
and told him to get the best accommo
dations east the country afforded.
Of "Bart's" galantry to women many
stories are told, the most interesting of
which is how : he played a game of stud
poker with a young lady passenger in a
coach that he had stopped, the stakes
being a kiss from the young woman if
beaten and the return of the money and
valuables of the passengers by "Bart"
if he was worsted.
In the spring of '72, "Bart" had been
doing a smashing business in more
senses than one in the northern part of
the state, and he had become such a
terror that a double guard was sent out
with every mail that went from Sacra
mento to Nevada City. Once the dar
ing Mexican attempted to capture a
coach against these odds, but
ONLY SUCCEEDED . * v-'
--in getting his left ear partly torn off by
a ball from a guard's ride and a flesh
wound in his left leg that was sufficient
to dampen his ardor for a while, and it
was several months before he was heard
of again. So long did he remain out of
sight the express and stage companies
began .to lessen their vigilance, and
once more the mails and "the strong
boxes were sent out with only one man
beside the driver to watch them. It was
generally thought that one or more bul
lets of the guards in the scrimmage had
taken fatal effect, and that the bold high
wayman had dragged himself away to
die in some of his mountain retreats,
northeast of Sacramento, on the east
side of the Sacramento river valley,
among the foot-hills of the Sierra . Ne
vada mountains, is a deep canyon at the*
head of which a mountain stream of
modest proportions tumbles over the
edge of a cliff or ledge making a beau
tiful fall known as The Maiden's Tears.
Through this canyon wound the Nevada
City trail, and over it once a week rattled
the heavy mail and express coaches.
Near the falls the trail lay across a great
open space with the stream on one side
and piles of huge boulders on the other.
A coach was crossing this space one
afternoon in August, a few months sub
sequent to the wounding of "Bart."
The guard on the seat by the driver was
dozing , ... •■.-.;.*
AND NODDING
in the heat of the summer sun, while
the driver was struggling to keep his
eyes open by whistling, shouting and
snapping leaves from the trees with his
long lash. Inside there were a dozen
passengers stowed away, among whom
was a young lady going to Nevada City
to teach school. She was plucky as
well as handsome, and four years as
teacher in the mining districts of the
West had given her a splendid knowl
edge of the ways and customs of the
rough element in which she was living.
The other passengers were business
men and speculators who had come from
the East to try their luck in the gold
diggings. The coach had just reached
the center of the open space when the
noose of a lasso, flung from among the
boulders above his head, set
tied over . the shoulders and
arms of the drowsy guard, and in the
twinkling of an eye he was hauled from
his seat and fell in a helpless heap in
the road. At the same time a deep
voice from among the rocks ordered the
driver to stop and throw up his hands,
which he did without a second invita
tion, and then the same voice ordered
the passengers, who had begun to stick
their heads through the coach doors to
ascertain what was the trouble, to step
down and out and hold up their hands.
They hastily obeyed the command and
were soon in line with their hands
pointing heavenward, the driver head
ing the "list." When they were well in
position "Black Bart," holding a revol
ver in one hand and the lasso in the
other, stepped -out from among the
rocks and came down to where the
coach stood. His
FIRST BOUND
the guard securely and then proceeded
to relieve the passengers of their money
and valuables, which he tossed into his
big sombrero that he had thrown down
by the side of the road. In the pocket
of a miner he found a pack of playing
cards and threw them with the rest of
his booty into his hat. When *he had
finished searching the passengers lie
said :
"You can put your hands down now,
gentlemen, lt must by kinder awkward
standin' in that position. I'm sorry to
put you to so much trouble, but you see
1 had to have money, and I thought this
was a pretty good crowd to strike. I'm
kind of ashamed of myself to put such
a pretty woman as this lady is to so
much inconvenience," and he smiled
apologetically at the young school
teacher, who surprised her fellw pas
sengers by smiling back at the robber
and saying, "don't worry yourself,
Bart, it was no inconvenience at all."
"You know me - Miss?" inquired
'Bart.'
"I've heard you described so often
that I telt pretty well acquainted with
you," replied the school teacher.
'Bart' seemed to be flattered. "I ad
mire your pluck," he said; "most women
faint when they see me."
"I never saw a man yet that I'd faint
for," replied the school mistress, to the
horror of the other passengers, who
were afraid that she would anger the
robber and he would shoot them off one
at a time just for revenge. But they
were stricken dumb with amazement
when she said: "I'll tell you what I'll
do, 'Bart,' I'll bet you that I can beat
you
ONE HAM)
at stud poker. If 1 don't you may kiss
me. If 1 do, you must let his coach and
its passengers go on unmolested. Will
you do it?"
The proposition seemed to stagger
"Bart" for a moment, but he recovered
himself and after a hearty laugh said:
"Waal, Miss, you beat any woman I
ever came across before. .1 never kiss
a woman unless she's willin', but if you
want to take them chances I'll play
you, but 1 reckon you you're giviu' me
the best of the bargain"."
The school teacher intimated that she
was really anxious to play for these
stakes and preparations were made for
the game. It was agreed . that the
driver should deal the cards, and "Bart"
insisted on the eleven passengers stand
ing up before him in a row twenty
paces away, so that he might detect
any attempt at treachery in time
to thwart it. The school teacher
seated herself on a mail pouch that
"Bart" had dragged out of the coach for
that purpose, and with his rifle resting
across his lap he settled himself on one
knee a short distance from her. Oppo
site them and between the players and
the line of passengers, on the ground,
sat the driver, who was to deal the
cards. "Word was given to start the
game and the driver threw the first card,
face down, to "Bart." The next fell at
the feet of the schoolteacher. Each
player was now entitled to four cards,
face up, and "Bart" caught the ace of
clubs, while to the teacher came the
seven spot of diamonds. The highway
man next caught the five spot of hearts
and his face flushed and he smiled con
fidently, for the first card he caught
was a five spot and he now held
a pair. The teacher drew the deuce
of diamonds. "Bart" could hardly con
tain himself when the next card that
fell before him was the live spot of
clubs. lie now had three fives, and he
was sure the game was his. At the
feet of the teacher fell the four spot of
spades. Her luck was,
;. INDEED WJIETCUED,
but she did not seem the least dis
contented when she looked over at
"Bart's" pair of five spots and then
down to her seven spot high. The last
turn came and the queen of clubs fell
in front of "Bart," while the seven spot
of spades was the teacher's winning.
She had a pair of . sevens . In sight.
"Bart" smiled. "I'm sorry your luck i
THE SAIKT PAUL DAILY GLOBE: SUNDAY MORNING, JULY 1, 188S.— TWENTY PAGE&
came so late," said he, ■'yon drew well
at last, but my three fives win the
kiss?" and he turned up the : "hole"
card, displaying his trio of five spots.
"You did well, Bart," replied the
teacher, "but your three fives don't
beat my three sevens," and, picking up
the "hole" card she showed him the
seven spot of clubs;; which gave her
the winning hand. The smile faded out
of the highwayman's face, but when he
realized that he had been fairly beaten
he helped the young lady to her feet,
smiled pleasantly, and said: "Gentle
men, I've lost a mighty big stake. Come
up here one at a time and get what be
longs to you out of that hat." Singly
the men came up and took their money
and jewelry. Their firearms "Bart"
kept. ''Bart" ordered them to get into
the coach, and he. handed the school
teacher in as carefully as might a de
votee of modern society. He ordered
the driver to his seat, unbound
the guard, and, at his command
the horses dashed up the trail, and thir
teen hour 3 later tho coach rolled into
Nevada City with its precious cargo in
tact. :,,;-..;;.-.,-:.".'-"
When the story of the school teach
er's pluck was told, the citizens . of Ne
vada City presented her with a hand
some gold watch, and the Wells-Fargo
Express company gave her a check for
$1,000. Twelve months later
SHE MARRIED .
the mayor of the town, and she is still
living in Nevada City, where her hus
band carries on a very successful bank
ing business</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014381/1888-11-28/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Between July. U875, and November 4,
LBBS, Black Bart robbed twenty-eight stages
in this State. For a time he made bis
headquarters i:i tliij city. He was arrested,
convicted and sentenced to a term in the
State Prison, from which he was released
on the 23d of last January. He went by
tbe name of C. E. Bolee, alias C. E. Bolton,
alias Black Bart, the Po-8. J. B. Hume,
the special officer of Wells, Fargo & Co..
who was interviewed by a reporter, says:
" During the time that C. E. Boles was en
gaged in robbing Wells, Fargo & Co., ex
tending over a period of eight years, he
lived in San Francisco at a respectable
lodging-house, and rei>orted or gave people
to understand that he was engaged in min
ing—owned a mine in fact. His brief ab
sences from the city.^when he would rob a
stage, were supposed to be necessary to
visit his mine, and his daily associates
never dreamed of his true character. His
habits, his appearance, his tastes and intel
ligence were all foreign to the generally
accepted idea of a stage robber and thief.
It is quite probable that he has adopted or
still continues the same modes of life, and
in any community where he may be a resi
dent is doubtless regarded as an honest and
law-abiding citiz=n. During his incarcer
ation in San Quentin he was seen and
noted by nearly every Sheriff then offici
ating iv the State, and could hardly fail to
be recognized by any one of them" in the
event of a chance meeting. He would be
known by all convicts who were in tbe
Penitentiary during the time of his im
prisonment, and all these facts lead to the
conclusion that it is highly improbable that
he has chosen this State as a place of resi
dence. He is an accotnplisl^d stage-robber,
aud pursued his business so long and suc
cessfully that we have no reason to believe
that he would be willing to earn hi 3 living
by actual, honest work, and the recent
numerous one-man stage robberies occur
ring in this State bear so many character
istics of the Po-B's artisticjhandiwork that
we are fuliy convinced thai he has resumed
bis former mining operations and is again
prospecting for bullion in our treasure
boxes
"He is too subtle and keen to risk sus
picion by selecting any small town as a
piece of residence, for tbe reason that his
frequent ahtences would be noted ami dis
cussed, and he would naturally desire to
avoid particulars in regard to his trips, his
mine, etc , and as it b a well known fart
this is much more difficult to accomplish
in a small town than in a city where one
scarcely knows the name of bis next-door
neighbor, much less bis business, habits or
porsnitt. For these seasons- we believe
that be has selected some snih city outsidf
of tbf State of California, as Denver. Kan
sas Ci'y. Omaba. Salt Lake. Tucson, or
even CbicagO or St Lonis. and, wiihout
creating surprise or suspicion, inakts these
periodical trips for the purpose of 'clean
ing up' iis Uiine and renlenishine his ex
chequer, and ihen returns to lead the same
apparently innocent, blameless life which
he pursued in San Francisco.
"About 11 a. m., Thursday. November
8, 1888, ihe staee from Downieville, in
Sierra county, Cal , to Nevada City. Nevada
county, was robb«ui by one man armed
with a Winchester rifle, at a point three
miles west of ' Nigger Tent' and about five
miles east of Camptonville. He robbed
tbe United States mail, taking the contents
of three mail bags. From Wells. Fargo &
Co.'s box be secured $19 40 in coin and a
gold bar valued at $2,200, described as fol
lows : Weight, 127.77 ounces; size, Oj
inches by 2 9-10 inches, and about 1 inch
thick, stamped on tbe bottom. ' H. Scam
nion ' across each corner and in the center.
The gold assays 880 fine."
On the 20tb instant be robbed tbe stage
from Eureka, Humboldt county, to I'kiah,
Mendocino county, getting $684 74 from
tbe express box and probably $1,000 from
tbe mail.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn97067613/1888-12-20/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Elnck Bart, the lone highwayman,
known to every resident of tho Oolden
Coast as ouo of the most tlnring and
desperato men on tho road, has since
his release from San Quentin prison, on
the l'Mi of last January, again taken to
Lis evil courses, and committed a series
of dar.ng robberies upon the Wells
Fargo & Co.'s stage coaches. His
caretr, says a b'an l'runcisco correspon
dent of tho Cincinnati Inquirer, has been
cue of romance and boldness, and his
fame riva's that of Dick Turpin and Six
teen String Jack. He is known as the
lone highwayman for the reason that he
has no eorariauions or Fa's. and always
committed his depredations single
handed and alone, and in such quick
succession as to paralyze the entire com
munity, and with such dispatch and
judgment as to baffle the brst detectives.
He robbed twenty-eigtt stages before ho
was caught, and since his release from
prison several robberies have been com
mitted in which his peculiar methods
are recc-gnized.
Of a tall and commanding figure,
lilackBait is sixty years of age. He
wears a heavy, drooping, iron-grny
moustache, witu a heavy imperial. He
lias beeu rine'.y educated, uses chnste
and elepant language, never indulging
in profanity, and while ho mado his
headquaiters in San Francisco he made
but few ac-iucintanoes, and those ouly of
tho best. He does not use intoxicating
liquors or tobacco in any form, nor is
he addicted to the use of opium. His
character is an anomaly, made up of all
that goes to make respectability and gen
tility, combined with the nerve dash and
darjug t the highway robber. His
dress is always neat and proper, and his
manners those of a cultivated gentleman.
Tho most remarkable peculiarity about
Black Bart is his fondness for writing
poetical epistles, which he leaves on the
lacsncked treasure boxes that he has
pilfered. While these do not display a
Ligh order of literary talent, yet tiiey
bear the unmistikablo ear-marks of
originality.
Black Bart began robbing California
stages in 1875 and continued in a series
oi daring solitary attacks upon stages
Tintil June 23, 1S3. Detectives scoured
tho country for him, and for a long time
ecu hi secure even no description of him,
They kuew that ho was no ordinary
criminal. lhe robberies occurred al
ways in unfrequented parts of the moun
tains and the robber was generally able
to ccncsl Lis identity. Ino first clew
was finally, after the robberies in Men
docino county, October 2 and 3, 1878,
furnished by a vromua. She was a Mrs.
McCreary aud lived with her family on a
lovely farm. Detective Hume was told
by her that a gentleman tourist had
passed that way tho dny before. One of
the woman's daughters had seen . and
waited upon him for lnneh. They were
positive that he was not a highwayman.
From this woman the detective secured
a tolerab'y accurate description, which
was sent all over California. Still the
robberies continned, but as the pitcher
that often goes to the well and the
prowler thnt is often rushed finally gets
broken, so Black Bart robbed one stage
too many and w,i3 at hist caught.
The detectives, from what they could
learn of the man, were convinced that
he dM not live in any of the
small towns of California, but must
when t leisure reside in San Francisco,
lU'J was probably a respectable-appear-
the lia'go -oviK5.riMo5C
rubbed three infles a bove'-Oopperopolis.
I. E. McConnell, the stage-driver, was
compelled to unhitch his horfes while
Blaok Bart was digging out the iron box
from under tho driver's seat';-with a
sledge-hammer. By chance a, iiunter
came a'ong where McConnell wasjstand
ing with the horses. He borrow.! Ilia
.iiii a'd opened lire on the roblcLl!!!!
lii.iir?i Icr file ijfuu wi l ti tie pi iji utier.
some HoJJW in goJU arnatgaui. Jrhe at-
tack was so sudden and unexpected that
Black Bart was disconcerted, 'and he
flew, leaving behind a pair of opera
glafses and a handkerchief, on which
was the laundry mark, " F X 0 7." The
mttelts were at once sent to ban Fran
cisco, and a'd the laundries of the city
were searcueu. ine aavs niter tlie
robbery the laundry was located, and i
was learned that tho handkerchief be
Jong-d to a gentleman named C. E.
BoitVn, resnhug at a Mrs. Webb's lodg
ing house, at .No. 27 Second street. It
was learned that Mr. Bolton had the
day before returned from his mines.
He was called upon by the detective, J,
T TT 1 . - .
x. name, -nno, on pretens-e or mining
uusiness, inancea mm to go to an office,
where he was arres'eil.
He was tried, convicted and sentenced
to the penitentiary, and served his term
of four years and two months, having
Decn oiscnarged on theXJu of last Janua
ry. Whilein prison he was a model convict.
ho obeye 1 all tho rules of the institn
tion Without a murmer. He was reti
cent in his habits and avoided
being seen as much as possible. He
made no acquaintances durinsr his con
finement, and had but one bosom friend
and that wns Carl lhorne, alias Dfirsey,
who, in company with John C. Patterson
brutally murdered tho banker, Win. 1
Camming, at .Nevada Citv. in 1879.
After leaving prison he spent some time
in San Francisco; then went to Modesto,
Merced and Visalia, and on the 2bth of
February he left Visalin, leaving his
valise wi.h tlie landlord, saying that he
would tend for his baggage at some fu
ture time. Since this time three stage
robberies bearing his earmarks hae
been committed, and detectives are
scouring tho country for him.
Black Bart's real nsma is Charles E.
Boles. He was born in Jefferson County,
r. Y., in 1&'50. He came to California
fl XI. II ' 1 . . -. , . . . .
niter me goiu excitement 01 !B4J or
about 18uO, and worked in the mines
witu some success in Butte, Eldorado.
Shasta and Trinity Counties. In 1853 he
returned .Last ivjd settled in Illinois
When the war broke out he lived at De
catur, where, early in 18C1 lie joined the
Una Hundred and Sixteenth Illinois In
fantry Volunteers. He gained some dis
tinction for bravery, und was made a
Sergeant. In 1865 he returned to his
home and sold his farm.locating his wife
and three small children, all girls, in
Oregon. Illinois, and started for Mon
tana. He worked for eighteen months
m tlie mines at Helena, and regularly
corresponded with his wife and fainilv,
end iu 1S67 wrote them that he Lad set
tled up his business and was coming
home. From this nothing was heard of
him by his wifo end family. She, from
lack of support, was forced to sell the
little farm and stock, and nt last was
compelled to resort to n.annal labor to
support herself aud deserted children.
bhe heard that he had been murdered
by the Indians, but womanlike, clunjr
i . . i , i . . . f3
irunuiuusiy 10 ine oeiiet tnat he was
live and she would sse him again.
After he was received at the San Onen
tin Prison, in lfcSi, his criminal career
was extensively published all over tho
United States, aud tho fact that the
name of C. E Boles was found in a Bi
ble in his room on Socond street at last
reach e I his wife, who was living at Han
nibal. Mo. Mrs. Boles at once wrote to
tho officers of the prison, inquiring if
tho robber was her long-lost husband.
A photograph wns sent to her, and she
at once recognized the picture as that of
her husband. Through all these years
she had been faithful to his memory.
His daughters had grown from little
toddlers to bo young women, and one of
them was married, und th mother was
living with her son-in law at Hannibal.
Despite the graphic accounts of Iiisn.any
and great crimes, despite the fact that
he wus then incarci rate. and occupying
a felon's coll, despite her long and con
tinued i-trnggle w ith poverty on account
of his heartless and brutal desertion, the
wife and danghters wrote him loving
ami affectionate lette:s, and urged him
to join them at the ch se of his imprison
ment aud pass the declining years of Lis
(d iu the bosom of lis famiyasnn
tinest mau. For a time h kept iip the
r spondence, and then, as tlie days
us incarceration drew to a close, he
i an insolent letter to his Eoa-in-law
lei the purpose of severing all connec
tion with his family. His wife offered
to join him at Sau Francisco, but the
officers informed the poor woman that it
would be no t'.se, as her husband would
havo no communication with her.
That Black Bart has gonu back to his
old profession is firmly b lit-ved by the
detectives and police authorities of San
Francisco. Tho lat-t. three robberies
bear the imprints of his genius. His
method of attacking a stage has always
bceuthoEnmo. A jump from thosida al 5he
road brought him in front of the leading
horses which sheltered him from the fire
of the mefsenger or driver. His double
barreled shot-gun would cover them on
the box, and they would seldom fail to
throw out tho treasure-chest and the
mail.
It is related of the English highway
man, Dick Turpin, that when, in the last
century, ho used to rob the stage coach
es going up to London he often danced
witU the lady passengers on the green
sward, and Black Bart, following in his
wake was always in his criminal exploits
very polite to" the ladies. Ho always
cavri d an old ax with which he opened
the treasure-box and a sharp knife for
the mail-bags.
At six o'clock last Tuesday night the
stage from Mendocino City to Ingrains,
the terminus of tho North Facilic Coast
Railroad, was stopped and robbed by a
lone highwayman. The robbery oc
curred at a point about seven mile3
north of Ingrains. Ordinal ily the stage
passes this place about four o'clock, but
the illn ss of one of the stage horses had
delayed it for two hours, and it wns after
dark when it was reached. John Almon,
the owner of the stage line, was on the
seat with tho driver. Suddenly a man
with a gun in his hand, stepped into the
rotid and ordered the driver to stop. He
had previously rolled a heavy log across
the road in order to block it. As soon
as tho stage was stopped the robber
ordered the driver to throw out the
express box and the mail bags of which
there wer three. When thi3 was dene ho
told the driver to get down and remove
the obstruction, and then allowed the
stage to pass on. It is supposed there
was little in tho express box but the mail
was valuable. There is one registered
letter which contained $300. Detective
Hume, of Wells. Fargo & Co., says posit
ively that the robbery was committed by
"Black Bart." If he had had any
doubts before as to the identity of the
"Lone Highwayman" this last robbery
would have rt-moved them. He judges
by the style of the robbery, for it was so
dark last niht that it wns impossible
to see tho Ligwayman's face; He de
clares that "Black Bai t" is tho greatest
stage-robber who has appeared on the
road since America was discovered, It
is a significant coincidence that "Black
Bart" stopped a stage at the same place
several years ago, aud on that occasion
left his first poem in the express box.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014381/1889-10-05/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Famous Highwayman Believed to
Have Left the Country.
San Francisco, October 4th. — It will be
good news to all nervous stace passengers
to know that Charles E. Bolton, better
known as "Black Bart, the P. O. S," has
left this part of tne country. Such is the
firm belief of the many detectives and
Sheriffs interested in finding the celebrated
robber.
He is a most incorrigible outlaw, and no
one will regret his departure. His recent
confinement of ov<=r tour years in Sau
Quentin apparently had no influence what
ever in inattdog u:m to mend his whys.
Within six months after his release, in
January. 1683, he was at his old tricks, and
since then at least three robberies are
known to have been his work. The offi-
•'- *! \ '
cers who lookpd the cases up arc thor
oughly satisfied that he robbed the Ukiab,
Shasta and Caiuptouville stages during the
past year. The Carajtonville robbery was
his last exploit. He then obtained a gold
bar worth $2,200, the property of ihe ex
press company. This has never been of
fered for sale, s j far a3 known, and the pre
sumption ia ihat Bart has too much discre
tion to negotiate for it in this country. He
is believed to have gone either to Chiua or
Australia.
The special officers of the express com
pany have lately sent out a number of
photographs of the "lone highwayman,"
and it is thought this agitation alarmed
him and made him decide to take a foreign
trip for his health. Over thirty robberies
of stages and express boies, beginning
ia July, 1883, are attributed to Bart, but so
shrewd was he that evidence sufficient to
convict was never obtained, except in two
or three cases. When he was finally
caught, in 1883, he pleaded guiliy and se
cured a light sentence.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn97071110/1902-03-14/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>There Is good reason to believe that
Black Bart, the boldest ud most no
torious highwayman ever 4nown to
California, is ope
rating again. Tbe
five robberies of
stage and coach on
louely mountain
roads In- northern
California and
southern Arizona
during tbe last few
mouths have abun
dant earmarks of
the famous lone
mm
tim--' wV-rs ,...J
BLACK BAHT.
keep pecking and pecking at Ic on ev
ery occasion and If occasions do nut
arise naturally, they make them. In
tys nagging, sarcasm, or Irony, bear
a leading part A thing may be said
once or twice as a pleasaut raillery, In
a genial humor, but when repealed
over and over It ceases to be fuu. It
then cuts. Sarcasm Is two-edged
tool; It cuts and wounas me out. , gUar.makjllg prevails.
whom It la aimed, and It lrrltatea ana j Cultjvator corregl)ondent supplies the
roughens tbe one who uses it. " '
dangerous tool for one to use who
wishes to be either kind or just It
comes easily0 to the Hps and tbe In
tellect takes a certain kind of delight
in aptness. Ingenuity or sharpness. Its,
use grows ou one. At least the bablt
becomes so habitual that It Is used
unconsciously. However good-natured
... eem to take It. It Is nlniost cer
tain to leave a sting; there Is a wound
that hurts. Struggle against It as oue
will, there will often be an Impression
carried that some part of It Is meant In
earnest
Too often do all of us wound the
feelings of others by carelessness In
highwayman of tbe ! speech. We cannot too eareiuny
Sierras. More tbuu i guard ourselves against the nagging
this, two of the passengers in the held- j habit It rasps and wears out tne
ud staeos knew something of Black ' host of dispositions. Let us endeavor
Bart when he held central California I cver to make our Bpeech kindly, even treeR three-eighths or one-half Inch
In torrnr 9(1 warn aim. and. from bis when ntiliced to find fault. A Plow
MAKING MAPLE SUGAR.
Method of' Gathering the Sop and
Botlinic the 8irnp.
Maple sugr and sirup are favorite
sweets the country over, and this fact
gives a general interest to some Infor
mation about the maple sugar Industry
which has practicnl value also for the
sections where this particular kind of
An American
following details:
The evapoiutor Is the first and most
Important consideration: The point to
be considered iu nu evaporator is the
one that can make the best sugar in the
least possibletlme with lbs least amount
I of fuel. Evaporators are made of gal
! vaulzed Iron or steel, copper or tin.
i They are usually supported on Iron
! arches lined with brick, but sometimes
i the arches are made entirely of brick,
j Storage tanks, draw tanks, sirup tajiks,
j buckets and pails are of galvanized
steel, tin or wood. We consider gat
vaulzed steel tbe superior article be
cause It will not rust. Bucket covers can
be of wood or tin; spouts, steel or tin.
Take a sugar place of 3,000 trees or,
rather, one that uses 3,000 buckets
Wheu the "boss" thinks It Is time to
"sugar," the men are set to tupping tne
GEO. P. CROVELL
Successor to 8. L. Smith,
' Oldest Established Hoss in the valley.
speech and figure, are sure that their j with a word
robber Is tbe noted bandit. Moreover, Mow with a i
r.o one seems to kuow what has be
come of blm sluce his release from
San Quciitln prison, where he b.id been
sentenced for elj,'ht years.
Tho trial of Black Bait for highway
robbery In Vlsalla. Cal.. In May, 1884.
revealed a mass of Information about
this unusual bnudlt. For 17 years high
way robberies by Black Bart had taken
place at Intervals and lu least expect
ed localities, all the way from Port
land, Ore., to Yuma, Ariz.
His arrest came about lu this way.
In March, 1884, the stage coach that
traveled the rough road over the deso
late hills and through the lonely
I bit is used, nnd In large trees the hole
Btrikes deeper than a ; g bore(j fl,out two Inches deep, lu
rord." We shall never smnner trees only about one ud a half
err bv sneaklnc too kindly. I uese inPhes. Snouts are driven or screwed
naggers are often kind at heart and : jn tmekets bung to each spout and cov
would not' willingly wound another. , erg lf tney have them.
They have formed the habit uncon
sciously and are not aware of how
frequently they Indulge In that kind
of talk. It does not occur to them
that any one may take a further mean
ing than they have meant, or that any
part of It will be taken seriously. It
Is unavoidable, however, that this Is
so.
" The nagging habit Is the real reason
why some women find It difficult to re
tain servants. It Is for tbe sharpness
of their tongues that some really ex
Some trees are tannend In two or
three and oftentimes four places, hang-
the making of a true American, for ha
would not acknowledge defeat What
be ?.-rote was 'This is know good.'
"It vras not until some time after
ward that I heard of this, when the
woman with the skin trouble was show- j
Ing me tbi copied charm. When I saw I
the trick the boy had played on both;
of them I thought my vindication had n n J nrnrAr'iAO
truly cotfie. But when I explained it ui V UUUUO, V4I VVVi iw,
.... . ... ,. .1 l. .. A..l.n.n - V a 41 .
all to ner sue met wuu me iu-iuw
argument:
"'Well, miss, it cured us both.'
"What could I say to tbnt?"
MISTAKES ABOUT LINCOLN.
He Was Not an Obscnre Public Man
When Nominated.
An Iowa writer who Is telling about
the number of great men which bis
State has produced In tbe past few
years snys that although Secretary
Leslie M. Show bus been only four
or five yenrs In politics, yet "he Is far
better known to the nation than Llu
colu wus when he was nominated for
President." Tbe notlou that Lincoln
wus unknown outside of bis own
State until bis nomination for Presi
dent has been expressed by better In
formed writers ibau the Iowa inun
here referred to. but It Is a delusion
just the same.
Lincoln served a term In Congress In
tht latter part of the Mexican war.
and though be did not make a national
reputation then, be was sufficiently
well known throughout tbe country In
1S5C. at the time when the Republican
party's first iintloual convention was
held, to get 110 votes in that conven
tion for Vice President on the ticket
DEALER IN
Boots and Shoes,
Hardware,
Flour and Feed, etc.
This old-established house wi'l con
tinue to pay cash lor all its goods; it
pavs no rent; it employs a clerk, but
does not have to divide with a partner.
All dividends are made with customers
in the way of reasonable prices.
gulches from a gold mining camp lu , peop,e are avol(le(1 and dlsllked
held up by a masked, loue highway
man; whom the driver aud all the pas
sengers recognized by his manners and
speech as none other than Black Bart,
Tbe veteran highwayman hod reduced
his mode of robbery to a science, and
when be had quickly harvested a crop
of gold watches, purses and bits of
Jewelry, he shouted to the driver to
go ahead.
j In society. People dread the tongue
j lashings that slip so easily from the
I Hps and without real malice, but they,
j nevertheless, cut deep. Let us put a j
' guard on ourselves and see that this j
bablt of sarcastic speech and nagging
Is uot ours. The Chinese have a say
! Ing that "A man's conversation Is the
1 mirror of his thoughts." There Is a
truth. In it. lf we habitually talk In
CHAPTER XVII,
As Mr. Dysart takes his way slowly
around the house, the sound ot running
footsteps coming toward bim from
side walk attracts his attention. It Is
Grunch. wild-eyed, haggard, her thin
gray locks, unbound through her unusual
haste, flying at each side ot her lean, for
bidding face.
"Mora haBte, worse speed," says he,
sarcastically. "Is the house afire, or my
precious nieces dead, that you rush upon
me with such Indecorous abandon?"
"Hush," says she, sternly, with a
glance behind her, "this Is no time for
words like those. Think only of this,
Dysart," pausing and panting for breath,
"that I have seen a ghost."
The old man laughs.
"Be silent!" hisses the woman savage
ly; "cease your gibes, I tell you. The
ghost I have seen Is Is "
"My worthy father, for example," sug
gests he, with a sneer. "No? Well,
come, who, then?"
"Michael Sedley!" Tbe words fall from
her as though they burn her lips in pass
ing. The sneer dies from Mr. Dysart's lips;
a dark flush suffuses his face, turning it
almost black for the moment to fade
presently beneath the ashen hue that
makes him look like a corpse a corpse
with eyes of fire! He staggers back
against a tree, and his hands catch con
vulsively at tbe bark ot it
"You are mad, woman!" he says, in a
terrible voice.
"Ay, may be. So I say. Mad I am.
It It was bis ghost I saw. But if I saw
him in the flesh, how then, Dysart? Why,
sane. Well," with growing excitemeut,
"shall It be mad or sane?"
"Mad, mad, mad!" shrieks he, furious
ly. "All my life you have been my bane,
my curse, and now, now ,what is this
news you would tell me? Sedley! Why,
be Is dead, woman dead, I tell you!
Where have you seen him? Speak, 1
command you," cries he, seizing her arm
and shaking her violently. -
"On the avenue. I was there watching
Miss Griselda, as you told me to, lest she
should go Into the woods again, when he
came slowly toward me through the
trees, prowling about. He's changed
he's gone to bone a deal; but I'd know
him still among a thousand. Ay, and
you'll know him. too."
It Is characteristic ot the iron nature
of the man that rose above all petty
cringings to a miserly fear that as he
enters the presence of the one creature
whom on earth he dreads, be does so
with a calm visage and one expression
less. His step Is slow, methodical as
usual; his face, gray in iti pallor, a very
mask. His brilliant eyes alone betray
the keen life that still lingers In the
gaunt old frame, and they look through
and through the unwelcome visitor with
aa unblinking gate,
"Yon!" he ssys, softly, nay smilingly,
extending a graceful hand, with a good
deal of languid Indifference.
"Jnst that" says Sedley, uv a tone so
loud and common as to contrast painfully
with the polished accent that had gone
before. "Years since we met mate.
"Many," says Mr. Dysart. sinking care
fully Into a rickety old chair near him
"And yet It seems like yesterdsy that
we parted.
. "Take it like that! it shows what
downy nest you ve been lyln In, says
the large, coarse-looking man, with
distinctly aggrieved air. "There's the in
justice ot It You've as much right to
this place as I have, when all's told. And
If I csnl get my aba
" 'Sh I" breathes Mr. Dysart, softly
lifting one band. "And well, so yon
have come back? Pining for the old
country, ear
"To look yea up," doggedly. "To
whether yon wers la th grave or out
f It partner."
"Partner t" repeats Dysart as If
gentle Interrogation.
"Ia crime."' roughly, as lf angered by
the other's tone. "That's what they'd
call It Drsart at the Old Bailey,
whatever court It might com before. I'm
att particular,
"No no," assents Mr. Dysart. with
gentle acouragement
"I aevsr blamed yon, mind yon that
But a lawyers a worriting sort o var
xnlnt A man should stick to his word,
aea L and when the old gov-aer refused
to stick to his, after all his promises to
yon. why. If yoa kept him to it ia spite
of him, whoa ho had ao longer power
to kick well, wko'a to say yoa were
wrong, ek?"
"Too are very good; very sustaining,"
says Mr. Dysart. slowly. His tone is,
porks pa, Hi tie f sin tor.
"Ay, that's what 1 am to then as
ataads by m. Aad yoa sad I a r hi tho
The Dahlia's History.
More than one hundred years ago
Baron Humboldt discovered the dahlia,
a small, single flower, in Mexico. Could
some prophetic vision have revenled to
him the dahlia of to-day In Its duzzllng
hues and varied forms he might, per
haps, have been prouder of that dis
covery than of all his other scientific
achievements. It was sent by him to
the Botanical Gardens, Madrid, where
It received the name of dahlia in honor
of the botanist Prof. Andrew Dahl.
The same year It was introduced Into
k Sim Jm 'MWm
Davenport Bros.
Are running their two mlll, plsuer and lioi
liciury, and can till oidun lor
Lumber
Boxes, Wood
and Posts
ON SHORT NOTICB.
THE REGULATOR LINE.
BOILING THE SYRUP AT THE CAMP FIRE.
A MEETING WITH BLACK BART,
When the coach had rumbled out of
sight ou the way down the mountain
side Black Burt turned his attention
England, where It was cultivated un- to splitting open tho wooden box con
ing n bucket to each spout, of course.
Then, the weather being right, the sap
runs, aud the trams are started as soon
as possible, for the quicker the sap Is
made Into sugar the better the sugar Is.
Men with pnlls holding sixteen quarts
vn tn Pflch tree, collect the sap and
' empty It into the draw tauk, which Is
; being hauled about on a "sugar sled"
;by a pair of horses. These tanks hold
anywhere from twenty-flve to fifty pall
! fuls. When a load Is secured, tbe team
1 is driven to the sugar houses, and the
! sap, by means of four-Inch pipes,. Is
i drawn from the draw tank to the stor
I see tank.
' " ' I The storage tanks are placed on a
a certain way, we grow to be tbnt way .taci,12 0n the outside of the sugar
In character. Milwaukee Journal.
der glass. For a few years It was lout
to cultivation, then reintroduced Into
England. Cultivation soon developed
the double form, and every color ex
cept blue. For many years the Ideal
dahlia of the cultivators was a per
fectly flouble, ball-shaped flower,
Those who remember the compact
flowers of thirty or forty years ago
know how nearly that Ideal was real
ized, and remember the deserved popu
larlty of the dahlia of that day. But
people soon tired of the regularity of
that type, and for a few years it was
neglected. Florists were giving time,
labor and thought to the development
of the rose carnation, chrysr nthenium
and other popular flowers. At last
some far-seeing cultivator recognized
the possibilities of the dahlia, and In
new, Improved and more beautiful
shades of color It resumes Its sway,
and to-day greets us In so many varied
talniug the Wells-Fargo Express Com
pany's treasure. Something must have
disturbed the highwayman wuue u
was gathering up the money from the
treasure box, for when the stage coucu
passengers had armed themselves at
the next station and hurried back to
the scene, later In the day, they found
among the debris of papers, empty
purses and wrappings of parcels a
linen cuff. Tbe robber eviuenuy uau
dropped It In a hurried tight to bis
refuge.
The cuff was turned over to the ex
press company detectives. They found,
after weeks of Inquiry, that the Indeli
ble laundry marks were those of a
Chinese laundry on Bush street In
San Francisco. When the detective
had learned from the Chinese laundry
man that the marks on the cuff indi
cated that It belonged to one Charles
E. Bolton, a regular patron of the
ltfiuse and connected with the evap-
Dalles, Portland & Astoria
Navigation Co.
and attractive forma that every taste laundry, they set about to hunt up
may be suited. London Globe.
He Koto from tbe Ranks.
Prince Chllkow, the minister for rail
ways In Russia, commenced his career
by making a tour of the world In order
to take note of all the latest Inven
tions, and especially to study the Inner
workings and control of foreign rail
ways. He first took a position as an
ordinary mechanic in the locomotive
works at Liverpool, and, after serving
some years as a laborer, was raised to
the post of railway guard, and after
ward station-master at a small suburb
an station. When "he returned to Rus
sia he again worked his way from me
chanic to station-master, and, after
working tor several years In the latter
capacity on the Trans-Caspian and
Varsovie systems, be was made In
spector general and Anally minister of
railways.
V Sacrificing Ho Curls.
A pat illustration of the sort of man
who "breasts the blows of circum
stance" Is -given tn a story told of a
dashing, handsome Englishman who
came to Canada In 1832, took up sev
eral thousand acres In tbe Huron tract
and began building a homestead.
He wore long curls, then the fashion
One day the mortar needed for the
building of the flrep'.ace lacked hair,
Mr. Ralusford cut off the "Hyperion
curls." chopped them Into suitable
lengths and mixed them In the mortar.
"Tbe chimney-corner to this day,
says "The Canada Company." "bears
testimony to the riches on the outside
of a cranium and to tbe bump of deter
mination they covered."
in
Hardly Sn.
In no situation, probably, la tbe stam
merlng Infirmity more calamitous than
tn making a proposition of marriage,
An exchange gives s this dialogue:
Mr. Stutterly to Miss Grace
M-ui-m-lB G-G-G-G-G-G-Grace, I I I
I w-w-w-w-w-want you to b-b-b-b-be
m-tn-m-m-my "
"What did you say. Mr. 8tutterly"
"W-W-W-W-W-W-Won't yon b-b-b b-
be iny wu-wu-wu-wu-wlfe. I I-I-M-l
s-s-s-s-s-saldr
"O, George, this la ao sudden!"
In
t l-olnc 'tsm Temptation.
Mother Johnny, have you been
swimming?
Johnny No'm. Honest I ain't
Mother Then what makes your hair
oo wet?
Johnny I got all aweaty runnln'
away from the boy that wis goin'
Bwlniaiin'. New York Journal.
Mr. Bolton. It came out that diaries
B. Boltou. who owned the cuff, was a i
quiet, unobtrusive, spare man of about
60 years. He lived In a modest and
quiet boarding house, where sedate,
old-fashioned business men had rooms,
and every one there was bis friend.
When a detective went to live In the
same boarding house he found that
Mr. Bolton was a studious mant lived
correct me, was a reauer oi uew
books, dabbled in poetry, and every
few weeks went away to visit one of
the several little mines about Califor
nia in which he had Investments. Bol
ton was an expert whist player, and
evidently he had traveled far and wide
In bis early life. His bobby was water
colors, aud be spent whole days In
painting bucolic scenes alone In his
rooms. Then when be bad dlued In
atyle along with the other bachelors In
tbe boarding house he went alone to
the theater, where he took tbe least
conspicuous seat He never got mall
and never sent letters, but be devoured
the dally newspapers at times. Never
theless It did not take the detective
long to connect this quiet, polished gen
tleman with the most dreaded outlaw
In California.
For 17 years he had kept half the
sheriffs and constables, a lot of detec
tives, and all the United States mar
shals lu California ceaselessly watch
ful for a fresh deed by Black Bart
He had many a time walked down to
a local bank carrying a snug fortune
In bis gripsack the proceeds of a re
cent affair out on "the road" past
hundreds of Sun Franclico people,
while they were excitedly discussing
Black Bart's latest hold-up.
Tbe outlaw was convicted and be
cause of his confession and apparent
determination to lead a new life he was
sentenced to San Quentin prison for
only eight years. lie was a model pris
oner, and be earned all tbe commuta
tions of bis sentence for good conduct
He was librcated In July, 1800. For a
few daya be lived In Sacramento, wait
ing, be aald, until be got some money
from Eastern relatives, when be meant
to go to Seattle aud earn an honest liv
ing. Then tbe man disappeared.
There la no doubt In the minds of
the officials who participated In Black
Bart's capture before, but that tbe ac
complished stage robber Is again at
work and will once more lead the of
ficers of tbe law a merry chase before,
he ia apprehended.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88085947/1909-09-15/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THREE THOUSAND A YEAR
JUST FOR BEING GOOD
Special Correspondence to The Press
SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 14.—
Does It pay to bo honest?
jj If you would secure an answer
; to that question, visit the offices
of Captain Seymour, head of the
detective bureau of Wells Fargo &
Co., in this city on the first day of
any month between the hours of
2 and 3 p. m.
If you do, you will meet a rather
neat old man, say between 60 and
70 years of age, who on entering
the room will walk up to the desk
of the veteran officer who has
brought grief to more express rob
hers than any man on the Pacific
coast, will exchange greetings and
will be handed a package contain
ing $250 in crisp bank notes.
Should you ask him, he will, if
he can be induced to talk, tell you
that honesty pays.
He ought to know what he is
talking about, for for 10 years past
he has been receiving $250 monthly
from the big corporation and all in
the world he has to do for the
money Is to keep honest.
This mysterious old man, If he
could be induced to speak further,
would tell you that his name is C.
E. Bolton. Rather an ordinary
name, but should you succeed in
getting deeper Into his history he
may be Induced to admit that he
is *no other than "Black Bart, P-S,"
that when in action he is rated one
of the most desperate highwaymen
that ever waylaid an express agent,
and that before he went on the
corporation payroll he cost Wells
Fargo nearly $100,000 In express
robberies.
He was finally caught, thanks to
the efforts of the late Wells Fargo
detective, Captain Hume, but after
his release the company so feared
his future efforts that they sent for
him, agreed to pay him $250 month
ly If he would rob no more express
boxes, the agreement was promptly
entered into and "Black Bart, P-S'
has been drawing his salary ever
since.
"Black Bart P-S" owes his title
Every Night Next Week
THE GORGEOUS PYROTECHNIC DRAMA
r 'The Siege of Jericho'
BY THE GREGORY COMPANY.
300—PEOPLE ON STAGE—3OO
GREATEST SPECTACULAR PERFORMANCE
EVER UNDERTAKEN IN THE
INLAND EMPIRE.
AT THE
Interstate
Fair
Don't Forget
MONDAY!
SEE THE BIG STREET PARADE OF THE
DRUMMERS' CIRCUS. STARTS AT 12
O'CLOCK FROM CORNER MONROE AND
SPRAGUE AVENUE. CHILDREN ADMITTED
TO FAIR GROUNDS MONDAY AFTERNOON
FOR 10 CENTS.
Bring the Kids
Bring Other's Kids
823 Riverside.
We have without ■ doubt tha
moat complete line of School Shoe*
In the city, In boys' youths' and lit
tle gents'. We have them In all
height*. Bach pair car
ries our guarantee) of sat-
Isfaotloh. Ask to see
them.
823 Riverside.
to the fact that on every express
box he robbed he placed this mys
terious sign. Accompanying the
mystic sign would always be a
verse written in a hand that look
ed like copperplate:
"Here I lay me down to sleep to
await the coming morrow,
Perhaps success, perhaps defeat,
and everlasting sorrow.
But come what may for better or
worse,
This box of gold has filled my
purse.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85038615/1913-05-25/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>How "Black Bart," the Train Robber, Deceived His Victims With "Dummy" Riflemen
"Black Bart," the train ronber, never used vio
lence. The shotgun he carried was never loaded,
and he never took a life or injured a human being.
He always worked aione, but by an ingenious de
vice he deceived his victims into believing that he
had with him a number of armed men.
With Jute bags or pieces of tent canvas he built
a screen about three feet high between two trees or
two pilee of rocks. The outside of thiB ambush he
carefully masked with branches of trees and chunks
of sod. Behind it he stuck in the ground half a
dozen sticks, and on each stick he hung a sombrero
and an old coat.
These hats showed above the amoush just aa
they would have if there had been real men under
neath them. Below each hat "Black Bart" stuck a
piece of broomstick painted black to give the oem
blance of rifle barrels. It all looked very real and
very formidable?for all the world as if six men
were crouching there with rifles In hand, ready to
fire at the first sign of resistance.
Time and again fast express trains on the west
ern roads would be stopped just at dusk in some
lonely spot by the frantic waving of a red flag.
When the engineer Jumped down to see what the
trouble was he was confronted by "Black Bart,"
dressed in a long linen duster 'and a tall, cone
shaped hat ouch ac clowns In the circus wear. At
the point of hi# shotgun the robber forced the ert
gineer and fireman to uncouple the engine and run
it a few hundred feet down the track.
By this time the passengers and trainmen wero
pouring out of the cars to learn the cause of the
delay. ''Black Bart" wasted few words on them.
Nodding his head significantly In the direction of
the ?'riflemen," whose hats and "gun barrels" showed
from the ambush at the side of the track, he said
loud enough for all to hear:
"Don't fire unless I give tne word, boys!"
The hint was quite sufficient. Convinced that
they were at the mercy of a large band of desper
ate men, passengers, trainmen and express messen
gers quickly handed their valuables over to "Black
Bart."
When he had secured all the plunder he uttered
a threat about not looking back on penalty of being
shot at by his "companions" and allowed the train
to move on.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1913-07-29/ed-1/seq-13/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>"BLACK BART, THE P08," WAS THE GREATEST
OF ALL BANDITS OF THE "WILD WEST'
'Don't Shoot, Boys," Unless Some One Fires First,
-By Frank Parker Stockbridge.
(Copyright, 1913, by' The Newspaper
Enterprise Association.)
A maij stage, lumbering, down the
Sierras' toward Sacramento..
Ajfigure by the roadsides-peaked
hat like a circus clown's, linen duster,
jute bagging wrapped' about his legs
looming tall in the twilight.
Back in the chaparral-half a dozen
other slouch-hatted, jute-legged fig7
ures, crouching.
'!Hands up!" :
The .driver throws his weight on
the brake, heaves his horses to their
haunches and OBEYS. The gaunt
man'by the roadside Bpeaks first to
the group in the chaparral:
"Don't shoot, boys, unless someone
fires first."
Then, to the driver:
"Throw out the box and the mail,
please, and line up. .the passengers."
.Down tumble the "box" the
Wells-Fargo treasure . chest and
the registered mail pouches. The
passengers scramble out. The bandit
apologizes profusely, solicitous es
pecially lest the ladies may be
alarmed.
"Drive on,!' he orders rtheir
money, safe in his- pockets "and
don't stop1 till you pass, the bend.
And," he adds, as the driver gathers
the reins, "if anyone asks who held
you up, here's my card!"
. He slips a bit of paper into the
driver's hand. The heavy Concord
coach rattles and creaks down the
hillside as the gaunt figure plunges
into the chaparral, treasure chest on
shoulder, mail pouches dragging be
hind. Around the bend driver and pas
sengers scan the bandit's ."card." Oa-</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1922-01-08/ed-1/seq-49/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A Story to Prove That
the New York Type of
Holdup ManHasMuch
to Learn Before He
Can Rank Profession
ally With Black Bart
worthy having freed himself of the euetody
of box and bag. "Drive on."
The men who were aent out from OroviDa
to rescue the box and the bag found in th"
rifled box the following bit of doggerel ver?e,
written, one may surmise, while the robber w.
lyii r in wait for the stage:
Here I lay me down to sleep,
To walt the comtn_ morrow j
Perhaps sncceas, perhaps defeat
And everlastinjr sorrow.
Tet come what wtll?ri] tn N w,
My condition can't be woreet
And If there's money ln that hem,
T_ money for my purse.
BLACK BART. ? O ft.
And thus Black Bart, staga robber, waa
ushered Into fame.
The descriptlon of him fnrnlshed by the
driver of the Russian River stage tallied wit''
the description of the robber of the Ororii!"
stage, including the note about a hollow voice.
By the last robbery he obtained a sum of mone"
marked "considerable" in the report of (he
expresa company given for publication. Thia
meant, decoded, about $5,000.
Black Bart had now rohbed the United
States mail, and his second exploit drew forth
an offer of $300 from the Federal government
for his arrest. $200 from the postal authori
ties and $300 from the Wells Fargo Company
As robbery succceded to robbery, each drew a
duplication of these offer.*, 6ntil the sum total
reached $18,000. where it. was left as a stand
ing offer. Twenty-five successful robberie
foliowed. The twenty-eighth, attemptcd
November 3, 1883, proved his undoing. H
had gone once too often to the well. Coli
stant success had made Black Bart carelesr.
An odd peculiarity was his seeming deter
mination to earn the second title lie bad he
stowed upon himself. that of P O 8. Thia waf
a little private joke over which hc chucklerl.
for he was perfectly awarc that he was no
poct. After nearly every robbery n hit o:
doggerel was found in thc- shattcred treasufc
box, in which he made some humorous allusion
to the attempts to capture him and defied the
owners of thc express company. saying he wac
trying to get a slice of the riches of "you
white-haired, Bonanza Kings." In those day
the expression "white-haired" was the equiva
lent of our "silk-stockinged."
The disastrous twenty-eighth robbery w?
committed on the road near CopperopoJU,
Calaveras County, thc Sonora to Milton stagf
being held up. It contained no passengers.
After obeying the order to throw out the
treasure box the driver was told to deseend
from his seat. He did so, and for nearly half
an hour watched Black Bart's efforts to open
'the box, which was heavily bound in iron. At
last he opened it and quickly threw amalgam,
gold dust and coin into a sack.
As he was making up his load an Italian
boy carrying a gun approached, unperceived
by Black Bart. The driver beckoned him to
approach, wtgwagging caution. The boy
obeyed, the driver took the gun and blare-1
away at the robber as he was disappearing
in the bushes. He ran rapidly out of sigbt,
but his hat was brurhed off by the overhang
ing bushes, and he lost a silk handkerchief.
The sack, the contents of which were valued at
$4,800, he hid under a log. In this sack was
the waybill, certifying the contents of the box.
and this bill bore bloud stains. Black Bart
had been wounded.
Here let me insert, out of its sequence, the
unknown peculiarity of Black Bart's robberies.
The gun with which he held up stages vtfai
never loaded. For seven years he had worked
a bluff with an empty gun. The gun he car?
ried wiien he held up the Sonora stage was
not loaded. Think of the nerve of the man!
There are things more powetful than guns.
One of them is a clew. The handkerchief that
Black Bart dropped in his fiight bore the
laundry mark FOX7. Hume employed Harry
N. Morse, former Sheriff of Alameda County,
but now head of a large detective agency in
San Francisco, to find the owner of the laundry
mark FOX7.
Capture and Confession
WJpOXT?" repcated the clerk at the laundry
office on Bush Street between Kearney and
Montgomery, to which place Black Bart's laun?
dry had been traced by Morse. "That is the
mark of Charles E. Bolton. I know him quito
well." To Morse's further inquiries the clerk
responded: "He's a mining man who altcr
nates between San Francisco and his mines.
He left this morning for his mines."
Morse explained that he wished to consult
Bolton as an expert on the value of some ot-?
in his possession, giving a flctltlous name?
Charles Richmond. He found that Bolton kept
a rocm in a small hotel, and, going there, made
a minute search. He found nothing more sus?
picious than a small, worn Bible, on the fiyleaf
of which was written Mary Bolea' inscription
to her husband.
This revealed to Morse two strong prob
abilities, to wit: 1, that Black Bart was Bol?
ton ; and, 2, that Bolton's real name waa Boles.
Therefore, when the owner of the laundry
mark FOX7 showed up at the laundry Morse
beguiled him by the ore expert trick into
Hume's office. "I knew he was Black Bart,"</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn95060797/1897-09-18/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>An Associated Press dispatch from
Olathe, Kansas, says: “Judge Burriss has sentenced James Gordon,
alias James Crone, alias ‘Black Bart,’
to the penitentiary for five years for
the crime of burglary.” The dispatch
further says that “
‘Black Bart’ was
raised in Kansas and is now not over
thirty-five years of age.” This will
be news to Hume and Thacker, as it
is to us, for we, as well as the two
special officers of Wells, Fargo  Co.,
have been all along under the impression that “Black Bart” was a much
older man. Evidently some snide
sneak-thief has been sailing under
false colors. Fourteen years ago, J.
B. Hume and Johnny Thacker and
many others, including ourself, were
on a “still hunt” for “Black Bart,”
and at that time —1883 —“Black Bart”
was represented to be a man nearer
fifty than “thirty-five years of age.”
And somewhere among our effects, we
still have a description of “Black Bart,
thepo-8.” However, if our memory
serves us right, the “po-8” was captured in 1884, sent to San Quentin for
ten years and released in 1894, and
after his release returned to Illinois,
his claimed state of nativity.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn91064030/1912-02-21/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1913-11-04/ed-1/seq-7/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/45043535/1902-08-01/ed-1/seq-18/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1913-07-29/ed-1/seq-14/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>"Black Bart, the P08."
That was the-scen- and the action,
late In 1877, of the first of the most
daring series of single-hand- hold
ups in the whole hiBtory of the "wild
west."
I write "single-hande- advisedly
for express detectives and post--
office inspectors, seeking clews, dis
covered that the figures In the chap
arral the "boys" who were ordered
not to shoot were Just sticks
draped with Jute bagging and topped
with, slouch hats.
Perfectly good bandits, though, in
the mountain twilight!
"All criminals are cowards" is a
police maxim. Rare is the thief who
dares to rob alone rarer yet one
who robs unarmed. But there was a
thief who robbed alone whose only
weapon was a pair of field glasses!
Twenty-thre-e times in the next six
years "Black Bart" lined up his
dummy "boys" in the chaparral in
the Siskiyou mountains, on the Oregon trail, back in his earlier haunt
in the Sierras. AlvCays scrupulously
polite to the ladies, not once offering
violence, always leaving his "card
a scrap of doggerel signed "Black
Bart the po8."
His express robberies netted him
tens of thousands nobody knows
what treasure he got from the mails.
Rewards for his capture were unclaimed. He was a bandit more cunning than the thief-taker- s. Only
once was a driver able to describe
him an American, about 50 years
old, with long gray hair, thin face,
deep-s- et eyes, prominent teeth and
dignified bearing. His language indicated education and good breeding.
Caution and courage go hand-in-haand "Black Bart" was caution
personified. With his field glass he
would watch a stage for hours no
difficult task in a mountain country
until certain none of the passengers' were armed. Then the quick
ambush, the rifled "box" and always
the disappearance without a trace
always until the laBt time.
Accident catches more-crook- s than
all the detectives!
On Nov. 3, 1883, it was accident
that a boy of the neighborhood rode
on the box with McConnell, driver
of the Yosemite mail stage, between
Milton and Sonora. An accident, too,
that the boy had a gun.
Near Sonora the boy dropped off.
A few minutes later "Black Bart"
cried "Hands up!"
"Where is the fellow with the
gun?" he asked McConnell. The
driver explained as "Black Bart"
started off with, his booty $4,400
gold in the express and mail sacks,
$550 in coin from the passengers.
But accident again the boy
came back!
McConnell grabbed the rifle and
fired four shots at the retreating
bandit. Next day detectives found,
beside a camp fire, a blood-staine- d
cuff and on the cuff were laundry
marks!
Here was the first real clew. They
searched thp laundries of every California city, and so, at last, they found
"Black Bart the po8." A quiet, Inoffensive man, E. C. Bolton, living in
an unpretentious San Francisco
boarding house. A "mining man"
so he explained his frequent absences. Identified as "Black Bart" he
confessed the last robbery, but denied the others.
TWO BLACK BART P08
But when Bolton went to San
Quentin "Black Bart the po8" ceased
to rob!</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84022044/1884-02-27/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Fruitless .Stopping of a Singe.
Sonoba, Cal., Feb. 26.—The stage between Sonora and Milton was stopped by
highwaymen twice this morning, the first
time by two men on the grade going up
from the Stanislaus river, about seven
miles from Copperopolis. The second
time by one man, near the scene of the
Black Bart robbery, five miles from Oopperopolis. The driver, Joe Mulligan,
threw out the wooden box, which was
broken open, but contained nothing, and
was returned to the driver. They were
unable to break into the iron treasure box.
Sheriff Thorn of Calaveras has gone to the
place of the robbery. The passengers and
mail were unmolested</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84024827/1903-05-01/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn95060905/1919-04-06/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86090383/1906-04-07/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn93051660/1902-03-18/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A PICTURESQUE HIGHWAYMAN
OF CALIFORNIA.
The Jekyll anil Hyde Career of a
Stage Kobber Who Terrorlaed the
Paci6c Slope and KludeJ the Official
for Many Yeara-Aga- ln at Work.
There is good reason to believe that
Black Hant. the boldest aud most notorious iiixliwaytuau ever kuowu In
California, is operating again. The
five robberies of
stage and coach on
lonely mountain
roads In northern
California and
southern Arizona
during the last few-monthhave abundant earmarks of VTfe the famous lone
tun highwayman of the
BLACK BART. Sierras. More than
this, two of the passengers in the held-u- p
stages knew something of Black
Bart when he held central California
In terror 20 years ago, and, from his
speech and figure, are sure that their
robber is the noted bandit. Moreover,
no one seems' to know what has become of him since his release from
San CJuentin prison, where he had been
sentenced for eight years.
The trial of Black Bart for highway
robbery iu Visalia, Cal., in May, 1884,
revealed a mass of information about
this unusual bandit. For 17 years highway robberies by Black Bart had taken
place at intervals and in least expected localities, all the way from Port-lau- d,
Ore., to Yuma, Ariz.
His arrest came about in this way.
Iu March. 1SS4, the stage coach that
traveled the rough road over the desolate hills and through the lonely
gulches from a gold mining camp in
the Sierras to Marysville, Cal., waa
held up by a masked, lone highwayman, whom the driver and all the pas
sengers recognized by his manners and
speech as none other than Black Bart.
The veteran highwayman had reduced
his mode of robbery to a science, and
when he had quickly harvested a crop
of gold watches, purses and bits of
Jewelry, he shouted to the driver to
go ahead.
A MEETING WITH
When the coach had rumbled out of
sight on the way down the mountainside Black Bart turned his attention
to splitting open the wooden bos containing the Wells-Farg- o Express Company's treasure. Something must have
disturbed the highwayman while he
was gathering up the mouey from the
treasure box, for when the stage coach
passengers had armed themselves at
the next station and hurried back to
the scene, later iu the day, they found
among the debris of papers, empty
purses and wrappings of parcels a
linen cuff. The robber evidently had
dropped it in a hurried fight to his
refuge.
The cuff was turned over to the express company detectives. They found,
after weeks of inquiry, that the indelible laundry marks were those of a
Chinese laundry on Bush street, iu
San Francisco. When the detective
had learned from the Chinese laundry-ma- n
that the marks on the cuff indicated that it belonged to one Charles
E. Bolton, a regular patron of the
laundry, they set about to hunt up
Mr. Bolton. It came out that Charles
E. Bolton, who owned the cuff, was a
quiet, unobtrusive, spare man of about
50 years. He lived in a modest and
quiet boarding house, where sedate,
business men had rooms,
aud every oue there was his friend.
When a detective went to live iu the
same boarding house he found that
Mr. Bolton was a studious man, lived
a correct life, was a reader of new
books, dabbled in poetry, aud every
few weeks went away to visit one of
the several little mines about California in which he had investments. Bolton was an expert whist "player, and
evidently he had traveled far and wide
in his early life. His hobby was water
colors, and he spent whole days in
painting bucolic scenes alone iu his
rooms. Then when he had dined In
style along with the other bachelors In
the boarding house he went alone to
the theater, where he took the least
conspicuous seat. He never got mail
and never seut letters, but he devoured
the daily newspapers at times. Nevertheless it did not take the detective
long to connect this quiet, polished gentleman with t lie most dreaded outlaw
In California.
For 17 years he had kept half the
sheriffs and constables, a lot of detectives, and all the United States marshals in California ceaselessly watchful for a fresh deed by Black Bart.
He had mauy a time walked down to
a local bank carryiug a suug fortune
In his gripsack the proceeds of a recent affair out on "the road" past
hundreds of San" Francisco people,
while they were excitedly discussing
Black Bart's latest hold-up- .
The outlaw was convicted and because of his confession and apparent
fleterniination to lead a new life he was
sentenced to San Quentin prison for
only eight years. He was a model prisoner, and be earned all the commutations of his sentence for good conduct.
He was libreated in July. 1S90. For a
few days he lived in Sacramento, waiting, he said, until he got some money
from Eastern relatives, when he meant
to go to Seattle and earn an honest living. Then the man disappeared</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-grover-shoe-factory-disaster</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1905-03-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BURSTS
FACTORY FALLS
FIFTY VICTIMS
iree Floors of Emerson Shoe Factory
Crowded With Employs Colla
Fifty to Seventyrfive
ORKED WHO LOST LIVES
MOSTLY WOMEN AND CHILDREN
of Sufferers Garry o
Over Half a Miter
ciaers wa HI gllings Destroyed
BROCJrQNs March 20 falling loss under horrifying
conditions is recorded result of a boiler explosion at the factory p
RB Grover Co makers of the Emerson
It Is estimated that from fifty to seventyfive persons have lost their
lives
The entire west halt of the was razed to the ground being
blown toward Calmar and Denton streets In the l 3rjSns wreckage were
200 to 300 pt the 400 people at in factory
The explosion occurred at 7foO a ni Fire broke out immediately
iA few minutes after the ruins were amass pfflames and
The front b the factory left standing by the explosion
caught lire driving out the rescuers from that part and making haste
essential for their e
C An hour after the catastrophe the large fqufstory factory was a blaz
ing ruin with fallen walls The Dahlbqr Calmar streets
the old Tavern building next to It on Main street
on Denton street and in that vicinity were blazing Al
den shoe factory on the opposite side of Main street was also oh fire
The fire was about 1030 oclock Raking over the ruins
for the dead began at noon Eighteen bodies have been taken therefrom
thus far
SHRIEKS HEARD HALF MILE AWAY
The cries and shrieks of those pinne d J landed head thin cottage dTt
ng4 Such a scene and such horror was
known Brockton before
The shrieks could be heard resounding
leariy tf halt distant Then the
lms of the explosion and the cries were
iushcd
The factory had been in two Tjy
xJistaht from the boiler
Thef side of the cottage was
crushed in by the immense mass 6
With bottom ripped out and tubes o f
the inside showing the boiler Ifes
the Hood house
Rumors were current that people were
Wile i hi the Rockwell and Hood linnsis
diirnK the flight of the boiler These
couht not be substantiated
part that settled to the the uiuer part The Hood xottage
our story f is the iviiole south rid crashed in
round was the west part of the factory M uro who i UKV IiiUe
Calmar street and that part running at the tih Is In tudf
Denton street at the rear was rernovtd to ti ileisfcborH next
The walls of this part of the factory She was uninjured but vasJ ersiders
crushed like an eggshell The ably shaken up by the occurrence
rittre structure careened away toward Estimated Damage
he streets and fell to the ground on tota lioss including the Grover fac
he Denton street side and to the second and it ta jltii ere in
on Calmar street sured the threestory Dahlbors bUek
On the fourth floor was the old TavQrn fclck both of
and the gang room Those irv the Seven dwelling houses
owcr floors are thought uffer damaged or destroyed br fire
d most loss Many making a fire less conservatively
upper floors were mated at about 350008
and beneath broken beams The u of Danlbors block
made their way out c F Dahlborg Co hardware and
Others were caught by the falling undertakers TV C Keith oigurs St
and could not get Many of ond story Mrs Hilda Morllrv aid fam
bv the rescuers who ill
smoking room o John JSrlckscn were seen of P Third floor hall
to thins had to abandon s h Belhany church
to their fate
Pinned in the Wreck Grocer Lost His Home
The rescuers say there were many After HfiSCUino Wife
saw In the collapsed factory
were pinned August Burgess a grocer at 29 Calmar
the machinery and were unable factory whose
get out house at the corner of Calmar and Den
Others whom willing hands would re
from danger could not be mm ed collapsed pait of anti
of some beam that held them
then the flames cane and the res
erp snaked were driven off while the cries of
un The thing J
pinned people were silenced in death thing was sore Oh it was errib1e
are many who made their way v house caUght fire My wife
of the wrccl beta a iliac hard
One man said there were a large num rkto her out the flames came so
girls from the stitching room is all gone I saved nothing
were gotten out or were able to
out of the wreckage Another Will
men crawling through the window
to safety VICtImS
Caught Under Machine
George T a decorator was
One man was under his machine when tQ breakfast in the lunch
comrade rushed to get him out H Hc was on Main street opposIte
him by the arm to drag hull when the shock of er
forth A burst of flames and a cloud of i
plcs
compelled him to let go and stag Vi as m front of the factory he
to a window He uirew himself out j said j when the came The
his own eir was broken in the fall whole building except the front part
Another man tried to get a woman blown outward and settled to the
across a room to the windows while ground
and fire poured about him He I rushed to help others get the people
compelled to abandon her and Jump ouu We got out ten or twelve people
from the window injuring himself ter Jf
ribly back blinding us and making it im
Caring for the Injured Kible
to The heat WaS ter
The injured have been taken to neigh i
pulled one woman out who was all
houS They are being cared Smoke
by physicians away We could do no more
All doctors In town have been called shrieks and the cries I shall
to the scene or to the hospitals The never forget them
service is busy and hacks
are being rushed from the stables to Rescuers Were Unable
carry away the injured q L TJviTl0
One doctor who came away from the
scene of the accident and went to a
to work said the accident was It was horrible said City Marshal
worst in all his experience and that W A Boyden one of the first to arrive
the Injuries to many of tile survivors after the fire alarm was sounded
among the most horrible he had ve were among the first to arrive
seen
scene We did all we could to
Boiler Flies Through Air rescue the people
The boiler which did the damage was There were many we could not get
located in the small brick boiler house to They were pinned down and could
in the angle of the factory which runs riot get out
T
Calmar and Denton streets When
It blew up the big tubular engine of de Keith Company Her body was cut in
structlon was through the fur two there In the ruins
toward the northwest We could do nothing One man we
crashed through the rear part of the
roof of the cottage house of Engineer In the effort
Axr TS M uWan thirty test and Then the flames ssemed to shoot from
i
psr
Perish
d
Res
Y
as the
from
c
cape
and
arid
The hurc
on i
uins by nah
t b 9J l l de fully JOO
no e
steeL
smol e enwrapped the VC asain st
he its nter and the RockweUs house was WtCkEd
11
d WP U
rte I heutil t
i
ra
s
The
stitching the busIness
corn wood to have
irts and women III were g
through stl
I
inQoW
j
out
esc Lode f
doa
b m
hom the
hOt beams or
In rear
o
streets the rear
l1io the the
whIch was saId
The shock of
uers me knew
skk long and we had
I
set
of nIt
o I
Never Forget
I
I Cries of
I
I irig his
t
rool
i
the factory the
1
Illo rUn
I
I
I
oo
the flames und smoke poured
out over the building and drove us
do more
u
cut It was
We dId all we could drove us
uThe
I T0 uccor e
I
I
U
on the
1 saw the wife of L nders
the the George E
launched
It dragged from the ruins wrenching
and tearing his from him
away 1c</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88085421/1905-03-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>FIFTY PERISH IN FACTORY FIRE
ROILER EXPLOSION WRECKS PLANT
Four Hundred Employes of a Shoe Manufacturing Concern
at Brockton Were in Great Danger front the Collapse
of the Building and the Flames that Broke Out
EROCKTOX, Mass., March 20 ?
Fifty lives are reported lost as the result of a boiler explosion in the Grover
Shoe company's factory this morning.
Two badly burned bodies have been
removed. Three floors collapsed and
the fourth floor filled with girls fell to
the ground. But most of the girls escaped by the windows.
All the doctors in town were called
to the scene or to the hospitals. Four
hundred employes were in the factory
at the time of the explosion. Part of
the boiler wrecked a house in the vicinity of the factory. The Are spread
from the doomed factory to the Bahlborg block and to several residences,
seven of which were destroyed. The
ambulence service and all available
carriages were kept busy removing the
injured.
The Drake tavern and Dahlborg
block were burned. The Churchill &
Aiden Shoe factories on opposite sides
of Main street caught fire.
The explosion occurred at 7:50. The
entire west half of the building was
razed to the ground. In the wreckage
were from two to three hundred of
the four hundred employes. Fire
broke out immediately. In a few minutes the ruins were a mass of flames.
The front of the factory which was
left standing by the explosion caught
fire, driving out the rescuers. An
hour later the whole factory was in
ruins. Many employes were caught by
the falling timbers. The rescuers were
obliged to leave them to their fate.
Those on the lower floors, it is
thought, suffered the most. At 9 a. m.
it was estimated that a dozen were
killed and 25 injured. Fifty employes
are missing.
The boiler which exploded had been
lying idle all winter. The fireman
who started the fire said the boiler
seemed iji a safe condition. He knew
of no cause for the explosion.
Forty are known to be injured, many
seriously.
Up to 11:30 25 bodies had been
taken from the ruins. Many were terribly mutilated and identification was
impossible. Most of the employes in
the main part of the plant escaped,
although in the terrible panic many
were injured. The Are is now under
control. The loss will reach $200,000.
Forty-two bodies have been recovered, all burned beyond recognition except five. It is believed the list of
dead will reach 75. The search is being rapidly prosecuted.
Up to 2 this afternoon 31 bodies had
been recovered.
The estimate of dead are now from
50 to 75.
The known dead are:
ALBIN DALBORG.
MRS. ELIJAH H. KELLEY.
LENUS SWANSON.
SAMUEL TILEY.
HARRY BARTLETT.
GEORGE SMITH.
DAVID ROCKWELL, engineer.
JOHN SMITH.
STEPHEN SNOW.
At 4:30 56 bodies had been recover- ed. It is now thought the dead will
reach 100.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn92053934/1905-03-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>KPLOSIOf! AND FIRE CLAIM
VICTIMS IN
Portion of Plant of R. B. Grover at Brockton
Wrecked by Blowing Up of the
Boiler.
TWO HUNDRED EMPLOYES ARE CAUGHT
Ruins Take Fire and Many Who Were Maimed Perish En
tire Establishment and Other Buildings Burn.
Brockton, Mass., March 20. Within
an hour after about 600 employes at
the R. B. Grover shoe factory began
work today the boiler blew up in the
engine room, wrecking a section of the
building and starting a fire which destroyed the ruins and spread to other
buildings nearby.
KttTIMATK OK !. I M I'OSIHl III.C
Owing to the nature of the accident,
the speed with which the flames seized
upon the collapsed section, and the ex
citement, accurate estimate of the loss
of life is impossible. It is understood
upwards of 200 persons were at work
in the department near the boiler
room.
IW IIOISKS III It .
Several dwelling houses and the
Dahlberg block, across the street from
the factory, were also destroyed. The
financial loss is estimated at $200,000.
Most of the employes in the main
part of the plant succeeded in escaping, although in a terrible panic. A
number were injured.
HIKTY III;. At 10:30 is was learned about fifty
were unaccounted for, and it was believed many of this number might be
dead or injured. The factory, a large
four-stor- y wooden structure, was destroyed.
MAY It KM II KIITV.
Brockton, March 20. Fire Marshal
Boyden stated reports made to him up
to noon indicated the list of dead might
reach 50,
Calls have been sent out for every
person who escaped to indicate the
fact at once. In this way it is hoped
a fairly accurate estimate of the number of dead may be obtained.
KIM 25 IIODIKS.
Brockton, March 20. Twenty-fiv- e
bodies have been taken from the ruins
up to 11:30. Many of them were so
horribly mutilated and burned as to
make identification almost impossible.
HA V K TIIIHTV-K- I VK HOIHKS.
Brockton, March 20. At 2:30 35
bodies had been removed from the
ruins. None were identified. The list
of injured numbered upwards of 50.
An official of the Grover company expressed the opinion possibly 100 persons will be found to have lost their
lives.
AffOI M' KOH ..
Brockton, March 20. At 3:15 42 bodies were recovered, and 250 of the 400
employes accounted for.
Mile rrnni l. Rrockton. March 2o. The factory
was situated altout a mile south of the
city proper. A series of alarms summoned all the fire apparatus in the
city to the scene. Aid was also sent
from nearby places.
The firemen experienced the greatest difficulty in battling with the flames
as the factory was of an extremely Inflammable nature and nearly all the
floors were saturated with oil.
Save Kmplurik
Their attention was chiefly given to
(he pan of the factory nearest the
Invller house, and in the early stages
of the fire a number of employes were
extricated from the ruins.
The flames, however, soon stopped
the rescue work, and the entire plant,
with those who failed to ese-aje-,
has
been abandoned.
Crowds (imhrr.
Meanwhile news of the accident had
reached the homes of the operatives,
and through the streets already near
the burning factory, nien and women
were struggling wildly towards the
center to get news of relatives. Cries
which sounded above the roar of the
flames were heard as frantic women
learned there was little hoie for anyone who was caught in the building.
Mai)' Went llnnir.
After the explosion many of the employes went to their home.. This add
el to the difficulty of compiling a reliable list of the missing. The Rrock- -
hospital was notified at once of the
disaster and hurried preparations were
made to receive the injured
All ambulances, police wagons and
many street carriages and physicians
and surgeons were hurriedly sent to
the scene.
Arrest Kniclneer.
David Rockwell, the engineer in charge of the boilr, has been detained
by the police pending an investigation.
Dencl and Mlnnlnst.
DAVID ROCKWELL, engineer, died shortly after being arrested.
JOHN SMITH.
STEPHEN SNOW.
Missing:
Frank Bell.
Harnabus Lewis.
Nellie Leary.
Maurice Fitzpatrick.
Mira Berger.
Mrs. Perry.
The injured:
Andrew Lundell.
Elmer H. Dodge.
Hiram Pierce.
Ira Buck.
George W. Lawrence.
Aid. George E. Mork.
"William McGaupe.
Joseph McLaughlin.
O. Reynolds.
William Emerson.
John Turner.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85052116/1905-03-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>FIFTY KILLED OR HURT
BY BOILER EXPLOSIONr
Shoe Factory atf Brockton Mass Blowna
Up Early This Morning
t
The Shrieks ol the Dying Heard Half a Mile Many
r Were Rescued
k
Uroifklon Mass Mar 2OSome6o aro dead and Injured an n result
of n boiler explosion wrecking and
Betting nflro tho It H Grover Co
Shoo factory at 760 oclock this
morning
The west half ni tho factory con ¬
taining between two hundred nnd
three hundred of hands was razed to
+
the ground
Tho front factory wax left stand ¬
ing and caught flro driving hack the
rogutnrs
In nn hour the four story factory
vas n blazing ruin
The adjoining business block build
lrg nnd seven hoiiBcjrwcro destroyed
Tho cries of persons pinned under
+
the timbers In the ruins were heard
tcarl half n mile
Then the flames and smoke on
wrapped tho victims and tho shrieks N were hushed
Many girls nnd women who wore
i
ithroughi the windows on ladders Others were pinned down and rescuers could notl
reach them
Jerry Clifford workman roscuc l
his son and another man boioro drIven
¬
back
Every physician hero tins been call ¬
ed and ambulances and carriages
tool time wounded away
Night Watchman Ncwhall who
firedl tho hotter says tho boiler hind
been Idle nil winter amid was first
used again Sunday
Ho says It wax In perfect condi ¬
tion with water In It when ho left
shortly before tho explosion
It Is cirtlmntcd that tho dcad In
the ruins number between fifty nnd
seventyfiveThirtyone kayo already been ta ¬
ken out horned beyond recognition
Tho fire was under control at
1030 and tho loss will be 1150000
Tho boiler was blown n hundred
yards and crashed through tho root
of 1Engineer Rockwells cottage
A story Is being used for a morgue</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045830/1905-03-21/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>SIXTY LIVES
Boiler Explosion Demolishes Large Shoe e
Factory and Incidental Fire Literally
Roasts Pinioned Victims.
DEEDS OF HEROISM AND SELF-SACRIFICE
One Man Hopelessly Caught Beneath Heavy Tim¬
ber, Calls on Rescuers'* to Save Others and
Lifts Several Girls t<| Safety Before the
Fire Reaches Hirrs. Brave Priest
Leads in Worl| of Rescue.
(Hy Associated I'rcss.) eTOa-r of an explosion. Al the same BROCKTON. MASS., Maroh 20.--j.'iaoir.ent the largo wooden frame of This city is in mourning tonigh; for ,1^. factory, a lour story structure', at least three score people whos'i ''quivered and then the roar portion of lives were blotted out early today by it?ebllapsc('.. the explosion of boiler large
shoo manufacturing establishment in
the Campello district, conducted by R.
Grover & Co.
The explosion was immediately fol¬
lowed by a Hash of flame, which con¬
sumed the factory, a long four-story
structure- as if it were a house of cards,
and incinerated an unknown number
of men and women, who were unable
to extricate themselves from a mass
of tangled wreckage, formed by the
terrific upheaval in the boiler room.
More than half a hundred of the em¬
ployes in .the building were maimed,
burned or bruised by the time they
reached safe ground. "
i*
Hert of a Veritable Inferno.
Some had jumped from the roof,
some from-.windows and other.3 had
boon injured in the mad rush to es¬
cape from tiie doomed factory, which
from all parts emitted the intense, aw¬
ful heat of an infeinn, driving back
the band of heroic rescuers who. in
few brief moments, bad performed
gallant service.
The fire extended from the factory In
seven other buildings in the vicinity
and destroyed them. One of the
buildings was a three-storv wooden
block owned by Charles F. Dahlborg,
the others being cottages of small
value, and a blacksmith shop.
Tw,o wooden dwellings near the en¬
gine room wore practically demolished
by the flying boiler, lint none of the
occupants was seriously injured.
The total financial kiss is estimated
at a quarter of a million dollars, $200..
000 of which Tails on It. 15. Grover k.
Co. The monetary losses are nearly
offSet by insurance.
Fifty Bodies Recovered.
It may never be known just how
many persons perished in the wreck¬
age. No ono knows exactly how manv
persons were in the factory. The num¬
ber has been estimated at four bun
died but Treasurer Charles O. Emorson, said tonight he doubled whether
there wore so many at work. Two hun¬
dred and fif-.y survivors have been ac¬
counted, for and at. midnight tonight
the remains of fifty bodies had bcei
recovered from the ruins, the search
j being continued all night. Fragments
of human frames which possibly might
belong to bodies other than those enu¬
merated, have also been found. Few
of I he -remains have boon identified.
Tiie head in nearly every case is missing and except in rare.'instances it was
impossible oven to distinguish the sex.
An inspection of the-wrecked boiler
by the State boiler inspector showed
that there was a sufficient supply or
water in it. The cause of the explo¬ sion is at present u mystery. The
disaster will be further investigated by
the State authorities. s
.-In p. fraction of a second this sec¬
tion of the great budding bad boon
transformed into a mass of iron and
Wood wreckage in the midst of which
Mcm.an beings were pinioned.
.; In another moment fire had broken
out in the debris and death by fire and
suffocation became the fate of scores
of the operatives.
Perpendicular Flight.
When the boiler exploded it passed
upward almost.perpendicularly, tearing
a passage as it went, killing many on
the way.
/After rising high in the air, it de-
.jtSjndetl. half the. distance and then
'swerving"northerly," cut its way" like
sjemo huge projectile through a dwell¬
ing house fifty feet away and pierced
another dwelling further along. 1cmolishit'g the latter t.tructure. Here
its course was stopped.
Scenes of horror. followed Die
wrenching apart of the factory build¬
ing. Ih» the rear the three lipper
floors- weighed as they wore with
heavy machinery, collapsed with a
crash that was hoard for blocks. Men
and women operatives working in de¬
partments of this section, who were
busy at their machine-:, had time but
to turn in an attempt to lloe after tnc
first, dull roar, when the flooring 'sank
beneath them- and they were carried
to tiie ground floor, crushed ami
bruised amid the mass of debris,
into Fiery Furnace.
Many fell into a veritable fiery fur¬
nace. In the sections of the factory
which remained standing the operalives were? panic stricken as Ihoy
sought to escape.
Many Hod down the stairways, and
reached the streets, others ran to the
windows, the fire escapes in many
oases having boon torn away by the
explosion. In desperation many jump¬
ed from tiie second ami third-story
windows to the. ground and wore dan¬
gerously injured. The crush on the
stairways resulted in numerous minor
injuries.
FEARFUL WORK OF
THE FiRE FIEND
Pinioned Victims of the Explosion, Un¬
able to Extricate Themselves.
Roast to Death.
EXPLOSION CAME
WITHOUT WARNING
Catattrophc Occurred Shortly After
the Operatives Had Bccjun
Werk- For the Day.
Uty AMSoclatcil I'rcss. > BROCKTON, MASS.. March 20..
The explosion occurred shortly after
the operatives had settled down to
work for tiie day bud boon begun
and came without any warning.
Suddenly the air vibrated with the
Scarcely bad the roar portion of the
structure collapsed when a tongue of
fiamo started up from the boiler pit
and. reaching out. as it ascended, com¬
municated with the splintered wreck-j age, and immediately afterward with
the standing walls. Soor, the entire
factory was in flames.
Instant- death was the fate of many
who went down with the floors that,
collapsed. A large number of ineii
ana women who were working near
the; supports were alive al';.cr the floors ami wälls fell
From these unfortunates thrilling
erics of agony and terror went up. Al¬
most all had been caucht. between
broken limbers, lighter wooden wreck¬
age ar.ddieavy pieces of .machinery.
Many Roasted to Death.
A few persons succeeded in extricat¬
ing themselves from the wreckage- but
more wen: roasted to death By this
time nearby citizens had arrived to
, 1905.
issist the employes who escaped in
he rescue of their fellows.
This task became momentarily more
lifih-ult and perilous, for tlie heat
roni ihe lire wr.s almost unbearable.
!*.}. tiie use of long pieces of limber the
¦cscuers were able to raise parts of
he wreckage- and thereby release
iome of Ihe imprisoned men and wo¬
llen and then, by rushing into the
uhoko. pul! them from the ruins.
Hc-cism and Self-Srcrifics.
Then it was that acts of selfsaoriicc anil heroism were seen.
One man whose legs was caught tin¬
ier en iron beam, cried to tin? res-
.uers that they could not extricate him.
mil to help lie girls behind him.
Sretohing out his aims he lifted sev¬
eral giils. one by one and passed them
lo Ihe rescuers. Then the lire reached
ilim and lie died.
A woman, who was entangled in a
shoe machine cried out that she was
lying and commanded the rescuers
Lo attend to others who might live. She
bogged to he shot. Scon the flames
enveloped her.
Brave Priest's Heroic Work.
An eng the first to arrive on the
scene was Key. .lames OTtourke. cu¬
rat i at St. Margaret's Roman Cat ho¬
le Church, nearby. At the risk of
lis life, he removed seven persons
Crom the ruins before the fire had
reached them and was returning for
lie eighth time when lie fainted from
;hc effects of the smoke and the shock.
Pal her O'KoMrke administered the last
rites of the church to many Catholics.
iKith to those who were saved and
seme who later perished.
FATHER OROURKE'S
THRILLING STORY
Priest Gives Heart-Rending Account
cf the Horrible Scenes Follow¬
ing the Boiler Explosion.
Father O'Jtotirke said tonight:
"Pinned beneath heavy pieces of ma¬
chinery, timbers and twisted .coils of
pipe."wTcfc-TOairySjh'.kt*-nwnyvaiiert-:a«-rfwomen, suffering terrible agonies
"In order to reach these imprisoned
sufferers we had to crawl through, tiie
debris and. with tlie aid of a large tim¬
ber, we raise! the wreckage which
held fast several men and women. In
this manner and by brute strength we
pulled out seven employes
"By t his time the flames were a
niest Upen us and we were about to
flee for safety, when one poor fellow
beggt'-l that a last effort be made to
save him.
Pulled Off His Leg.
Throe of us grasped the man by his
shoulders and arms and tugged and
pulled until suddenly"he cried: "'My
God. my leg is pulled off.'
"It was terrible, especially so be¬
cause a moment later, with our cloth¬
ing scorched, wo were ordered away
by the chi?f of the fire department
and were reluctantly compelled to
leave the poor man to his fate.
"Just before leaving I saw fifteen of
tlie imprisoned operatives, some al¬
ready suffering untold agonies from
the flames- which were actually cook¬
ing their flesh, and others watching
with terror-stricken eyes tlie fate of
their companions, knowing that a mo.
nient or two would bring to them simi¬
lar suffering, and then death."
Relatives Ask For Information.
With tear-stained and'haggard faces
women and children besieged tlie rec¬
tory of St. Margaret's Roman Catho¬
lic church, -during the day. pleading
with the. priests for it format ion about
husband, father, sister or brother who
failed to return 'home. Little com¬
fort could be given to these people.
At the Campelio police station a si¬
milar scene was enacted.
ICaily in the day Mayor Keith, fore¬
seeing tlie confusion which would en¬
sue, posted notices in conspicuous
places, requesting all employes who
had escaped to go at once to the- police
station and give their names.
Names Posted.
'I hose names were Immediately post¬
ed, and around this list of names hov:
ered a throng of women.many l:ys:
tcricai with grief because the list did
not include a relative. Back and forth
from the ruins to the station house;
and from station house to the ruins,
these grief stricken women tiled, in a
never ending procession, looking' at
the fragments of fiesh and bone as I hey
were placed in pine boxes and hurried,
away to the morgue. Only in extreme¬
ly rare casts was there the slightest
chance of identification.
Twenty-Niae Missing.
At midnight, a list, of twenty-nine
missing persons was given out a! the
i a:\\\pllo polit e station. There is good</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058130/1905-03-22/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text> Died sitting in his chair
	Engineer of Grover Factory Had No
Chance to Escape
IDENTIFIED BY HIS WIFE
FULL EXTENT OF THE BROCK
TON DtSASTBR
W WWV VWVIJI P
IVisfied that there was no chance of recovering additional bodies from the ruins of the R E Grover com
panys shoe factory ea rch wa
abandoned at 11 oclock tonight by
the 9niHlI army of volunteers after thirtyseven hours of constant
toll
The revised list as given out by
the police at 1130 oclock tonight
was ae follows
Bodies recovered K identified
14 missing 4ft reported escaped
KX It now seems probable that
hut fourteen bodies will be burled
with their identity positively established
An inquest be held shortly
That the llftylive dead repre
xent the toUt number of victimsno one familiar with the disaster
believesIJnockton Mass March retUJxllon of tho extent of the disaster
wlil h had come to the city of Brock
tot yesterday in the wrecking of the
foo factory of the R B Grover com
Imy and the ensuing terrible loss of
1 fr caine clewrly to the citizens todav
v lien they awoke to a full knowledge
o the hotTors attendant upon the cat
U Tpplie
All nigSUt the work of searching forth bodies of victims of the explosion
pud fire continued With unremitting
E
1 The work not rewarded after
ivmlnight by tho Hading of any additional bodies until 7 oclock today
vv u the remfelms of human being
VWTP found in the boiler pit Coneider
Jtig tho mystery regarding the disap
prarance of David Rockwell the en
pinrer who was In dharge of the boiler
ivhirh exploded the potice believe the bony found today woo that of the en
KiiferV fareful search of the boiler pit
the remains were found resultIng in the finding of a watch the rub
thiing all of which were dhown to
Rockwell the wife of the engineer
Ufrw identified by her as belonging to
Jirr husband Then the police found a
of a chair with a pelvis of human
une in it from which they Inferred that Rockwell was sitting beside his
boiler when the explosion came and
waR killed instantly The police are itisfied thAit the report yesterday that fw engineer had been taken out alive
v is duo to the confusion of Rockwell vith another employe
The body of Stephen Snow 83 years
cH one of tine oldest workmen in the plant was Identified today by
fcis son
The remains supposed to be those of engineer mude the fiftyfourth body
thus far taken from the ruined fac- tory The figures at rand today showed tliat about 260 persons wiho were at
In the factory when the explosion
v urred had been accounted for andtiit between fifty and 100 persons are
Ji sing
VKli reference to the cause of the
up of the boiler Josiah F
asstoCant engineer of the Brock tu sewage station who was with En
fiimer Rockwell at the Grover factory
it minutes before the accident occurred said todby that wihen he left RKkwell the steam was below the ntvty limit and there was plenty ofT itrr in the glasti but that he was run
i fIg Ute old bofler
The poHce In explaining the ulure of a number of employes to re Trt their escape cited an instance
iiKih indicated to them that many
tie workmen were dazed after the ex
pioBion Joseph Jones employed in hing room escaped with a few 1ruises In a confused state of mind i walked to another shoo factory In
iiie city applied for and was given einI and in a mechanical way he worked througdi the day Not until he
rt turn d to his home and found his amily mourning him as dead was the rgfrns brain ler enougn to enable him
to recall the incidents of the day When the boiler plowed its way upward tough the factory many operatives
v rre blown to pieces it is believed and hiis is offered as accounting kt port
discrepancy between the number of Jiodics recovered from the ruins and the j iMbr reported missing
the Brockton City hoapita1 and the TrTer hospital todey it was reported
all of the injured passed a fairly Portable night and were</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045830/1905-03-22/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text> Fifty Nine Found in Brockton runs 
	of That Number Only Fourteen
Have 8een Positively Indentified; Many Missing.
EFFORTS TO R4ISE PCÜ0F FUND
Workmen in Similar Trades Expected
to Subscribe Several Thousand Dol¬
lars. President of the Grover Company Prostrated When Told of the
Number Killed in Disaster.
CHy Associated Prpse.)
BROCKTON. MASS.. March 21
Satisfied that there was no chance of
recovering additional bodies from the
ruins itf the R. B. Grover Company's
shre factory, starch was abandoned at
11 o'clock tonight hy the small army
of volunteers, after 27 hours- of oon-
?ian> toii.
Although the polite and Medical E>:-
aminer Paine feel sure that they have
removed from the debris all remains
which wore net reduced to ashes, a
second search shortly wili be institut¬
ed to satisfy relatives and friends of
fho victims.
Reluctantly Leave Morgue.
The little band of persons who have
besieged the morgue since the first
lt!«ly was taken from iho ruins, re¬
luctantly turned their steps homeward
tonight, satisfied that all that remain¬
ed of missing ones occupied the pine
lioxt s inscribed "unknown"
At midnight for the first time since
yesterday Dr. Paine and his assistants
lenoined alone with the unidentified
dead.
The revised list as giver, out by the
police at 11-30 o'clock tonight was as
fol lows:
Bodies recovered: Identified. I I; un¬
known. 45; missing. 4S; reported as
(sen pod. 2S3.
Fourteen Identified.
It. now seems probable that hut 1-1
liodios will be buried with their iden¬
tity positively established.
An inquest will ho hold shortly.
Today saw the first movement on
the part of the workmen in trades si¬
milar to that pursued by ihe victims
iif the disaster to raise a relief fund
for the bereaved families. It is ex¬
pected several thousand dollars will
he subscribed.
NOW KNOW OF
HORROR'S EXT£.NT
Snd Truth Brought Home to Brockton
People by Tragic Evidences of
Monday's Catastrophe.
(Bv Associated Press.;
BROCKTON. MASS.. March 21..
For the first time since the fatal ex¬
plosion razed the shoe factory of R. B.
drover & Company, the people today, seemed to fully realize the enormity
of the calamity. This has been brought
about by the positive identification, by
'nils of clothing or otherwise, of sev¬
eral bodies and the failure to return
home of those who, had they stir
vi'ved. must before this, have bought
their friends.
Snow Turns to Rain.
A snow storm that early today cov¬
ered the wreckage tonight turned into
rain. but. braving the element, groups
of men, women and children, gathered
-.;(. the morgue, hoping against hope
that the chance discovery of a bit of
familiar clothing, or objects of per¬
sonal belonging; would lead to the
identification of their dead.
At ihe-ruins a hundred men. drench¬
ed t ? the skin, toiled unceasingly amid
the half burned timbers for fragments
of !,csh and bone, which, when found,
were hurried to the morgue to be scan¬
ned by those waiting there.
Mi-y Never Find Some Victims;
'1 hat the lii'ty-five dead represent the
total number of victims, no one fami¬
liar with the disaster believes. It is
extremely doubtful, however, that
more than fragmentary pieces of other
bodies will ever be found. Medica! Ex¬
aminer Paine said tonight that lie be¬
lieved ether bodies had been reduced
to ashes and the number of victims
might never bo positively known. He
<lid not believe that further identifica¬
tions of the charred remains at the
morgue were probable. Every body
wh^cli, had on it any trinket or piece of V
new;
clothing has boon more or less pdsilively identified.
Remains which have been placed in
1 fixes and marked "unknown" rite in
such a state that there is iio possibil¬
ity of their'being re'.'Ognizod.
BOILER WAS OLD,
SAYS OLD EXPERT
Engineer With Rockwell Five Min¬
utes Before Explosion, Say<?
Gauges Indicated no Donger.
(By Associated Press.)
L'ROCKTON, MASS. March 21 .
With reference to Hie cause of ihe
blowing up of the boiler in the Grovcr
factory. Joshua F. Gibbs. assistant enginoei at the Brockton Sewage stationwho was with Engineer Rockwell at
tiie Grover factory five minutes before
the accident occurred, said today that
when ho left Rockwell, the steam was
heiow the safety limit, and there was
plenty of water in the glass, but he
was running the old boiler.
The State boiler inspectors were
here today and devoted considerable
time to a minute inspection of ihe
heiler particularly with rt-ference to
any possible weakness in its construc¬
tion.
Expects Heavy Damage Suits.
Treasurer Emerson, of the Grover
Company, said today that undoubtedly
Heavy damage suits would he institut¬
ed against his firm.
Captain R. B. Grover. president of
the R. B. Grover Company, who has
teen ill for several weeks, was inform¬
ed today of the loss of life which at¬
tended the destruction of his factory,
lie was temporarily overcome, hut was
better tonight.
Captain Grover was told yesterday
of the destruction of his factory, hut
not of the loss or life. At that time,
he exclaimed: 1 am glad no lives
were lost. Had there been. I should
have felt it my duty to care </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1905-03-22/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text> UNERAL GLOOM
VEILS BROCKTON Councils Name Comm ittee
to With Citizens
3r
CHURCH SERVICES THURSDAYl
Grand Cortege Contemplated to March
to Cemeteries All Business
Will Be Suspended
BROCKTON Mas March a
spec ial joint meeting the citygov
ornmcnt last night called by Mayor
who presided the following joint
resolution was passed
Whereas a great calamity has fallen
upon people arid the people of our
sister towns In the sudden destruction
of the R B Grover C6 factory with
scores of human lives lost under con
ditions the most heartrending and ter
rible crushed out by falling of the
floors and walls or swallowed by pits
less and relentless flames
Resolved That In the shadow o tills
great catastrophe which athwart
every heart and darkens so many
mourning homes we tender the be
reaved our deepest sympathy in this
hour of affliction sharing as we may
their sorrow and bowed with them in
one common grief and it is
Councils Name Committee
Ordered That a committee consist
ing of his honor the mayor three
members of the board of aldermen with
such as the common council may join
be appointed to take such action in this
sad exigency as they shall deem proper
and to act in conjunction with any
committee or committees which
appointed for such purpose on the part
of our citizens or of any
The meeting voted to close the city
departments city hall and the schools Thursday and to require all places
business to be closed at least during
tho hours of the funeral services
The special committee held a meeting
ai the close of the joint services and
formulated a plan for the formation of
the funeral cortege which promises be
cause of the large number of organiza
bens desiring to join it to be a tre
mendous affair
The committee will take up later the citys share in forming the relief fund
Funeral Services Tomorrow
Public funeral services for the
will be held tomorrow afternoon and
Mayor Keith has suggeste that the un
Identified bodies be buried in the city
cemetery
Altogether fiftyfive bodies have been
recovered and the police report that
there arc still thirtyfive employes miss
lug
Just how many of these perished in
addition to those whose bodies have
found Is a matter of conjecture
but It is believed that many of them did
their bodies being completely consumed
Medical Examiner Payne says
From what I have seen of the ruins
I am convinced that nothing but ache
r main of many of the operatives
were caught in oho factory and whose
bodies were incinerated in the terrific heat So undoubtedly many never will
be accounted for since all physical evi
dence of their fate will be obliterated
OnlY sixteen of the charred bodies have been Identified and the under takers moved the unidentified to a tem
Continued on Fourth Page
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045830/1905-03-22/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Fifty Nine Found in Brockton runs 
	of That Number Only Fourteen
Have 8een Positively Indentified; Many Missing.
EFFORTS TO R4ISE PCÜ0F FUND
Workmen in Similar Trades Expected
to Subscribe Several Thousand Dol¬
lars. President of the Grover Company Prostrated When Told of the
Number Killed in Disaster.
CHy Associated Prpse.)
BROCKTON. MASS.. March 21
Satisfied that there was no chance of
recovering additional bodies from the
ruins itf the R. B. Grover Company's
shre factory, starch was abandoned at
11 o'clock tonight hy the small army
of volunteers, after 27 hours- of oon-
?ian> toii.
Although the polite and Medical E>:-
aminer Paine feel sure that they have
removed from the debris all remains
which wore net reduced to ashes, a
second search shortly wili be institut¬
ed to satisfy relatives and friends of
fho victims.
Reluctantly Leave Morgue.
The little band of persons who have
besieged the morgue since the first
lt!«ly was taken from iho ruins, re¬
luctantly turned their steps homeward
tonight, satisfied that all that remain¬
ed of missing ones occupied the pine
lioxt s inscribed "unknown"
At midnight for the first time since
yesterday Dr. Paine and his assistants
lenoined alone with the unidentified
dead.
The revised list as giver, out by the
police at 11-30 o'clock tonight was as
fol lows:
Bodies recovered: Identified. I I; un¬
known. 45; missing. 4S; reported as
(sen pod. 2S3.
Fourteen Identified.
It. now seems probable that hut 1-1
liodios will be buried with their iden¬
tity positively established.
An inquest will ho hold shortly.
Today saw the first movement on
the part of the workmen in trades si¬
milar to that pursued by ihe victims
iif the disaster to raise a relief fund
for the bereaved families. It is ex¬
pected several thousand dollars will
he subscribed.
NOW KNOW OF
HORROR'S EXT£.NT
Snd Truth Brought Home to Brockton
People by Tragic Evidences of
Monday's Catastrophe.
(Bv Associated Press.;
BROCKTON. MASS.. March 21..
For the first time since the fatal ex¬
plosion razed the shoe factory of R. B.
drover & Company, the people today, seemed to fully realize the enormity
of the calamity. This has been brought
about by the positive identification, by
'nils of clothing or otherwise, of sev¬
eral bodies and the failure to return
home of those who, had they stir
vi'ved. must before this, have bought
their friends.
Snow Turns to Rain.
A snow storm that early today cov¬
ered the wreckage tonight turned into
rain. but. braving the element, groups
of men, women and children, gathered
-.;(. the morgue, hoping against hope
that the chance discovery of a bit of
familiar clothing, or objects of per¬
sonal belonging; would lead to the
identification of their dead.
At ihe-ruins a hundred men. drench¬
ed t ? the skin, toiled unceasingly amid
the half burned timbers for fragments
of !,csh and bone, which, when found,
were hurried to the morgue to be scan¬
ned by those waiting there.
Mi-y Never Find Some Victims;
'1 hat the lii'ty-five dead represent the
total number of victims, no one fami¬
liar with the disaster believes. It is
extremely doubtful, however, that
more than fragmentary pieces of other
bodies will ever be found. Medica! Ex¬
aminer Paine said tonight that lie be¬
lieved ether bodies had been reduced
to ashes and the number of victims
might never bo positively known. He
<lid not believe that further identifica¬
tions of the charred remains at the
morgue were probable. Every body
wh^cli, had on it any trinket or piece of V
new;
clothing has boon more or less pdsilively identified.
Remains which have been placed in
1 fixes and marked "unknown" rite in
such a state that there is iio possibil¬
ity of their'being re'.'Ognizod.
BOILER WAS OLD,
SAYS OLD EXPERT
Engineer With Rockwell Five Min¬
utes Before Explosion, Say<?
Gauges Indicated no Donger.
(By Associated Press.)
L'ROCKTON, MASS. March 21 .
With reference to Hie cause of ihe
blowing up of the boiler in the Grovcr
factory. Joshua F. Gibbs. assistant enginoei at the Brockton Sewage stationwho was with Engineer Rockwell at
tiie Grover factory five minutes before
the accident occurred, said today that
when ho left Rockwell, the steam was
heiow the safety limit, and there was
plenty of water in the glass, but he
was running the old boiler.
The State boiler inspectors were
here today and devoted considerable
time to a minute inspection of ihe
heiler particularly with rt-ference to
any possible weakness in its construc¬
tion.
Expects Heavy Damage Suits.
Treasurer Emerson, of the Grover
Company, said today that undoubtedly
Heavy damage suits would he institut¬
ed against his firm.
Captain R. B. Grover. president of
the R. B. Grover Company, who has
teen ill for several weeks, was inform¬
ed today of the loss of life which at¬
tended the destruction of his factory,
lie was temporarily overcome, hut was
better tonight.
Captain Grover was told yesterday
of the destruction of his factory, hut
not of the loss or life. At that time,
he exclaimed: 1 am glad no lives
were lost. Had there been. I should
have felt it my duty to care</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn89067390/1905-04-06/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Shoe Factory horror
	Nearly One Hundred Killed by
Boiler Explosion.
Brockton, Mass. The list of dead in
the explosion in the R. B. Grover ft
Cc. shoe factory Monday morning may
resch 100- Sixty bodies have been re--
corded so far and seventy-fiv- e addi- -
tional operatives are unaccounted for.
Ftw of the bodies have been Ideoti-- 1
fied, as most of those recovered cai--
not be recognized. Thirty-si- x persons
were injured, many of them, It is be--
mortally. It is believed nearly
a! of those reported missing will be
found to have perished in the building
The work of removing the bodies has
been going on all night.
When the boiler exploded it passed
upward almost perpendicularly, tear
ing a passage as it went, killing many
on the way. After rising high in the
air it descended half the distance and
then, Bwervlng northerly, cut its way
like a huge projectile through a dwell- -
in,1; house fifty feet away and pierced
another dwelling further along.
Scenes of horror followed the
wrenching apart of the factory build
ing. In tho rear the throe upper floors
weighted as they were with heavy
machinery, collapsed with a crash
thai was heard for blocks. Men and
vomen working In departments of
this section who were busy at their
machines had time only to turn In an
attempt to flee after the first dull roar
when the flooring sank beneath them
and they were carried to the ground
floor crushed and bruised amid the
mass of debris. Many fell into a ver
itable fiery furnace.
In the sections of the factory which
remained standing the operatives were
panic stricken as they sought to escape
Many fled down the stairway and
reached lue street, others ran to the
windows, the firo escapes in many
cases having been torn away by the
A
explosion. In desperation many Jumped from the second and third story
windows to the ground and were dangerously Injured. The crush on the
stairways resulted In numerous minor
injuries.
Scarcely had the rear portion of the
structure collapsed when the flames
started up from the boiler pit and
communicated with the splinters of the
wreckage and Immediately afterward
with the standing walls. Soon the en
tire story was In flames.
Many acts of sacrifice and heroism
were seen. One man whose legs were
caught under an iron beam cried to
tne rescuers that they could not extrl- -
cate him and to help the girls behind
him. Stretching out his arms he lifted
several girls one by one and passed
thrm to the rescuers. Then the Are
reamed mm and ne died. A woman
who was entangled in a shoe machine
ci led out that she was dying and commanded the rescuers to attend to oth
ers who might live. She begged to be
shot- Soon the flames enveloped her.
Among the first to Arrive on the
ccene was the Rev. James O'Rouke,
curate at St. Margaret's Roman Catho
lic church. At the risk of his life he
removed seven persons from the ruin
before the fire had reached them and
was returning for the eighth when he
fainted. Father O'Rourke administer- -
oil the last rites of the church to many
Cal holies, both lo those who were sav--
ed and some who later perished.
Mayor Edward H. Keith personally
superintended the search. Treasurer
jO. C. Weston of the Grover company
ertimated the loss on the factory at
$200,000 and the loss on the other
t urned structures was placed at about
$50,000. The Grover factory, machln- -
ery and stocks were insured for $200,609</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn92073050/1905-03-28/ed-1/seq-12/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Lesser Events of Last Week.
At Brockton, Mass, the boiler in
the G rover Shoe Factory blew up
and sixty lives were lost</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn96076817/1914-07-04/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82016014/1905-03-21/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>54 DEAD.
This Morning's Figures on Brockton
Boiler Disaster.
Brockton, Mass., March 21. A realization of the extent of the disaster which
had come to the city of Brockton yesterday in the wrecking of the shoe factory of the R. B. Grover company and the ensuing terrible loss of life became
more clear to the citizens today when
they awoke to a full knowledge of the horrors attendant upon the catastrophe. All night long the work of searching for the bodies of victims of the explosion and fire continued with unremitting zeal. The work was not rewarded after midnight by the finding of any additional bodies until 7 o'clock today when the remains of a human being were found in the boiler pit. Considering the mystery attached to the disappearance of David W. Rockwell, trie engineer, who was in charge of the boiler which exploded, the police believe the
body found today was that of the engineer.- Rockwell was reported to have
been rescued yesterday badly injured and later to have died, but the police were not able to subsequently locate his
body. It seemed more likely to the police today that Rockwell, near as . he
was to the exploding boiler was among the first to. meet death. The body of
Stephen Snow. 83 years old, one of the
oldest workmen in the Grover plant, was identified today by his son.
The finding of the remains supposed to be these of the engineer, made the
fifty-four- th body thus far taken from
the ruined factory. The figures at hand
today showed that about 260 persons who were at "work in the factory when
the explosion occurred had . been accounted for and that between 50 and
100 persons are missing. A more careful search of the boiler pit, in which the remains were found today resulted in the flndihg-o- f a watch, the rubber heel of . shoe and a torn piece of cloth, all of which were shown to
Mrs. Rockwell .the wife of the engi
neer who identified them as belonging to
her husband. Then the police found a
part of a chair with a pelvis of a human frame in it from, which they inferred that Rockwell was sitting beside
his boiler when the explosion came and
was killed instantly. The police are
satisfied that the report yesterday that
the engineer had been taken out alive
was due to the confusion of Rockwell
with another employe. With reference to the cause of the
blowing up of the boiler, Josiah F.
Grubbs, assistant of the Brockton sewage station who was with Engineer Rockwell at the Grover- factory five
minutes before the accident occurred
said today that when he left Rockwell
the steam was below the safety limit
and there was plenty of water in the
glass, but that he was running the old
boiler.
The police today in explaining the
failure of a number of employes to report their escape cited an instance
which indicated to them that many of
the workmen were dazed after the explosion. Joseph Jones, employed In the
stitching room escaped with a few
bruises. In a confused state of mind
he walked to another shoe factory in
the city, applied for work and was given employment and in a mechanical
sort of way he worked throughout the
day. Not until he returned to his home
and found his family grief stricken and
mourning him as dead was the man's
brain sufficiently clear to enable him to
recail the incidents of the day.
When the boiler ploughed its way upward through the factory many operatives were blown to pieces it is believed
and this is offered as accounting in part
for the discrepancy between the number of bodies recovered from the ruins
and the number missing.
At the Brockton city hospital and the
relief hospital today it was reported
that all of the injured passed a fairly
comfortable night and were doing as
well as could be expected.
Medical Examiner Payne who has
been at the ruins of the factory almost
continuously since yesterday morning
today said he was convinced that nothing but ashes remained of many of the
operatives who were caught in the factory, so that undoubtedly many victims
never will be accounted for.
Shortly after 11 o'clock another body,
the 55th. that of a woman, was discovered in tha debris. A body at the
morgue was identified as that of Granville Hartwell, 40 years of age. an operative, who was prominent throughout the city and a leader among the labor
unions.
Mayor Keith announced that the unidentified remains would be transferred
to the East Elm street theater building and that the public would be permitted to view these bodies beginning at 1 p.
m. in order that all possible means of identification might be afforded.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86092356/1905-03-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Dcfcctivc Boiler Causes
Death of Fifty People
Special to The Oil Review.
Brockton, Mass., March 20..
A boiler explosion occurred at R.
R. Grover company's factory
this morning. The entire west
half of the building was razed to
the ground, being blown toward
Calmore and Denton streets. In
the wreckage were 200 to .'J 00 of)
the 400 people employed in place.
Fire broke out immediately anxl
within a few minutes the ruins)
were a mass of flames, and in
half an hour only the bare walls
were left standing. Such a scene
of horror and grief was never
known in Brockton before. The
shrieks of those imprisoned in
ruins were heard above the roar
of the flames. Many of the girls
employed in the stitching depart¬
ment on the upper floors were
rescued, but many others were
caught under the falling debris
and rescuers could do nothing but j
abandon them to their fate. The
extent of the casualties is yet un¬
known. but it is estimated that at
lease fifty were killed. Several
bodies were taken from the ruins
burned beyond recognition. Theboiler was used for the first time
early yesterday mornin? accordin? to the statment of the night"
watchman who had fired the
boiler, and heated factory before
leaving at 7:20 this morning, at
which time he was relieved by
Engineer Rockwell. The watch¬
man said the boiler was apparent¬
ly sound and every thing was
running smoothly with plenty of
water in boiler when he left. The
explosion* occurred at 7 :50 o'clock.
Estimates of dead now vary
from 50 to 75. The fire was un¬
der control by 10:30. The search
of the ruins is now going on, and
within a short time eighteen bod¬
ies were removed from the ashes.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1905-03-26/ed-1/seq-45/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BOILER SOARED IN AIM,
Left Death and Destruction in Its
Wake in Brockton Shoe Factory.
It probably will never be known exactly hois.
rrar-.y lives were loot
through the explosion of a
boCez last Monday in the shoe factory of R. B
Grover & Co.. at Brockton. Mass. The mere
or '.ess mutilated bodies of fifty-five persons
were found, but only sixteen of these could be
identified. Nearly fifty persons are reported to
be still missing. Besides these scores were tajure'l. Fire and the heavy machinery hi use
on
•
ifour floors of the factory
contributed to
th* loss of life. The explosion occurred a short time after
work had been resumed for the week. At the
moment the engineer was sitting Ina chair by
the window of the engine room watching his
engine. Suddenly there was a roar. Th* air
vibrated arid the older of the two boilers la the
factory rose from its foundations and tore Its
way through the four stories of the rear part
of the wooden factory. The air outside quivered
and the wooden frame of th« entire factory
trembled. Crushing lives out as it rose, the
boiler in a moment emerged from the roof and
soared perpendicularly into the air. As ft descended in some way its course . was changed.
Itshot off In a northerly direction toward the
engineer's home, near the factory, It tore Its
way through the upper story as ifit had been
a shot from a 13-inch gun, and pierced another house beyond.
The heavy machinery on the demolished floors
of the factory crashed downward, pinioning:
employes who had not been caught bythe debris
left by the
flying boiler. Then a flam* swept
from the Idler pit. a: imany of those who
had not been killed omrljjht were roasted to
death Intho fire that swept
through th* structure No one willever know Just what th* direct
cause of the explosion was, for the engineer
lost his lire.
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85047084/1905-03-21/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BROCKTON, Mar. 20. A boiler exploded today in the Grover
yesterday, In company with Dr. Cooper, Mr. Van Dine called upon Governor
Carter to lay the plan before him and
enlist his aid.
As outlined, the plan of Dr. Jordan
is to import mosquito-eatin- g fishes from
the mainland, thus destroying the insects in the larval stage. There are
fishes, Dr. Jordan say3 and he knows
more about fishes than anj'body in the
world that will "do this, much more
effectively than the kinds now here,
and he has offered to find a man who
will catch them and send them to Honolulu if the mosquito campaigners
here will pay the man's expenses.
The fishes Dr. Jordan Indicates."
said Mr. Van Dine yesterday while he
was waiting to see the Governor, --are
the varieties known commonly as killies
and top minnows. They come, mostly,
from Texas. Dr. Jordan recommended,
moreover, that we import several va--
Shoe Factory in this city, and was
pleted the disaster. It is thought
bodies have been recovered.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86075271/1940-12-26/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn78000873/1905-03-23/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE BROCKTON HORROR.
\ Boiler Kxplosion in llie iOrover shoe
factory, followed by Fire, Causes great
loss of Life.
Brockton, Mass., Mar. 20. The
3ity of Brockton is in mourning, tonight, for at least three score of her
•itizens, whose lives were blotted out,
parly today, by the explosion of a boiler
in a large shoe manufacturing establishment in the Campello district conducted by the K. B. Grover Co. The explosion was immediately followed by a
flash of flames which obliterated the
factory, a long four-story structure, as
if it were a house of cards, and incinerated the men and women unable to
extricate themselves from a mass of
tangled wreckage formed by the terrific upheaval in the boiler room.
More than half a hundred of the employes in the building were maimed,
burned or bruised by the time they
reached safe ground. The loss of
property is estimated at $250,000. The
Grover factory, machinery and stock
was insured for $200,000. Only 7 of 53
recovered bodies could be identified; 46
people are missing and 53 injured.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063778/1900-08-29/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014248/1925-08-26/ed-1/seq-12/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-building-titanic</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85042462/1908-04-23/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WHITE STAR LINE TO BUILD
BIGGEST SHIPS YET PROJECTED
By Associated Press.
LIVERPOOL. April Two new White Star liners which will be the
largest vessels yet projected will be
laid down at Belfast next June. The
exact measurements of the steamers
have not been given out/but they will
be over 840 feet In length, 78 feet in
breadth and with a gross tonnage of
45,000, or 50,000.
The ships are to be fitted with combination turbines and reciprocating
engines guaranteed to maintain a speed of twenty-one knots. The names
of the vessels are to be Olympic and
Titanic.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1908-10-02/ed-1/seq-9/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Englishmen Fear 60000Ton
Boats Cant Be
Docked
LONDON Oct 2 British shipbuilding
experts are puzzled to know how the
White Star officiate will land passengers and cargo lines two prospective 80000 tonnars the Titanic and
Olympic
The Mauretanla and Lusitania of not
much more than half the proposed
crafts tonnage have no more room
than they need to get through the
Ambrose channel and Into the Mersey
nt Liverpool
The popular opinion here Is that a
vessel of 0600 tons would have to
do Its loading and unloading at sea
Marine statisticians have figured that
the tonnage of the entire Spanish
of 129 which tried to land
an army In England in Queen Eliza reign was only 50139
Considerable progress is being made with construction work on the Olym- pic In Harland Wolffs yard at Belfast but the Titanic keel blocks will not be laid until January
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1909-01-03/ed-1/seq-59/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>ONE MILLIONFOR A STARTER
After an expenditure of J1.C00.000 the great stee!
j double gantry which willbo the cradle of th» larg-
!est two steamship In the world ha« been finished
I
at the shipyards of Harland & "WoifT.
at Belfast.
Ireland. The steamers whose keel blocks haT»
Ibeen laid side by side in this the biggest gantry
jIn the world are the Titanic and th« Olympic, of
| the White Star Line, and within a
year or two
Ithese leviathans willb« running between New Tori*
!and Southampton.
Soon after the two fast Cunarders. too LuslItaria and the Mauretania, had demonstrated that
Ione could travel in luxury and at a very high
ispeed through tha agency of turbine engines. th«
White Star X-in» announced that it would build
two steamers to beat the Oinarders la length and
breadth, and perhaps In other ways also. Itwas
reported at the tim» that th« new Whlta Star
\u25a0 liners would be a thousand feet inlength, but subsequently it was officially announced that they
iwould bo 900 feet lons, with a beam of ninety feet.
'
j When It was decided to build them it was found
that there was no gantry In thm world big enough
!to accommodate such monsters, and It was then
. that H&rland & Wolff began to rip up three of Its
', largest gantries and build the hug* steel and con-
'
crete cradle that Is now ready to bold th* Olympic
•
and the Titanic.
Before th* steel structure which supports th*
i powerful electric travailing cranes was erected a
'
big concrete base, twenty fret thick, was built upon
sp!le3 driven fifty fe«t into tha ground. The concrete foundation, in addition to being more firm
than the regular earthen
base, has the advantage
of cleanliness, an1 tools and materials which mar
fall from the cranes la the course of construction
may be found more readily. Parts of deck fittings
end tools have fallen into the ground la gantries
' with earth bases and have not been recovered
until the vessel has gilded from Its cradle into the
: water.
The construction of the Olympic has been started.
'
' The keel of the Titanic will be laid soon, and
visitors to the shipyards at Belfast will have an
opportunity of seeing the simultaneous csnstrcs-
. tion. side by side, of the largest two steamers tn
;
the world. The gantries are so built that
any
piece of material, however heavy or
awkward, may
[ be placed and held In whatever position the conatructora desire. The gantries themselves are more
than a thousand feet in length. 3C3 feet high and
something more than two hundred feet la -Ki&X
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1909-05-30/ed-1/seq-59/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>t.
TWO XEW GIAXTS OF SEA
lie Largest Steamships in World.
Although what will be the largest two steamships
In the world, the Titanic and the Olympic, of the
White Star Line, are mere skeletons just now in
their Lie million-dollar double gantry at Belfast,
Ireland the marine architects know exactly bow
they are going to look when they start on their
maiden passage to this port. From the plans and
specifications the designers have made a wush
drawing showing bow 'he monsters will look when
In the water and ready to sail. Although at nrst
glance the illustration suggests the Isauretania and
Lusitania. with their four gigantic funnels, there
Is something in the appearance of the new leviathans that Is typical of a White Star steamship.
The great height of the new liners and the broad
sweep of the bridge elves some idea of their 80.J80
tons displacement. The builders have almost eliminated the old cusr im of carying masts, «nd In this
respect the targesi ships in the world resemble the
Old Dominion steamers, tha smallest passenger
carrying vessels in the American coastwise service.
All the old Dominior Mners have only one mast.Thrse tw< vessels are being built simultaneously
sid* by side In a steel gantry that was begun a
year before the keels were laid, and which cost
over a million dollars. The new liners will each
n«» S» feet long, with \u25a0 92-foot beam. The unusual
beam la equivalent to the length of some of the
fast utenrn yachts of this port. The Olympic and
Titanic will iw» read] for the New York. Southampton an.i Cherbourg *»*r\im of the White Star
IJne in 1911. The builders are Harland a Wolff.
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn93063916/1910-01-08/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE WORLDS LARGEST VESSEL VESSELTHE VESSELTHE ESSEIJTHE
THE TITANIC NOW NO BEING BUILT
Here la an architectural picture of the steamship Titanic which Is being beingbuilt beingbunt beingbuilt
built for the White Star line at Belfast also a view of the giant steel cradle cradleiu
iu which the ship Is being constructed The keel of the steamship Is seen in inthe inthe inthe
the lower photograph The White Star company Is to have two of these theselaviathans theselebtthans theseleviathans
leviathans and they will be In commission early in 1911 Their launching launchingwill
will UI signalize a most important era in marine achievement for they will be bobyc beby beby
byc byctil by all odds the largest vessels in the world The Titanic and Olympic will willench wUlh willeach
each h be SCO feet f t in length 92 feet beam 45000 tons register and GOOOO tons tonsdisplacement tonsdl tonsdlstixccnwnt
displacement dl Ilem nt These enormous dimensions are best expressed In comparl comparlS
30115 S The Washington Va hlngton monument is r x55 > 55 5 feet high and the Metropolitan tower towerlit
lit New Xt York rliy r f ity rises TOO feet Tbe combined tonnage tonnn e of tbe Olympic Olympicand OIrJ11pllukl <
and Tlrxink k far fn r exceeds the tonnage ton n e of all It II the vrbs vessels tssl els ls engaged pn n ngld tM1 on both bothskies bothkles bothskies
skies In the hlsi hI Irlt + rl < conflict of the Spanish armada HfuJ dn Hud nd It Is even more In Interesting Inttresrln inttirestinx ¬
teresting to know ihir t t the Santa Maria was only em I rIt ii 0 feet fi Plat i t Ions IOll a and d 233 tons tonsvet tonhtnhn tonelnirien
htnhn t vet tat nn thl visw yf f 4r1 1 Columbus Journeyed TO th thp < new UP world</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045433/1910-01-23/ed-1/seq-14/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>SHIPS TO BE LARGEST
Vessels Under Constructionin Belfast to Surpass All
FOR TRANSATLANTIC SERVICE
Olympic and Titanic Will Have Ton
nnsre Twice as Great an the Maure
tania and Lnnitanla and Former
Will He Ready for Launching In
Anjfimt Other Year Later
London Jan 22 While the navy
of various governments are
trying to outdo each other In the buildingof mammoth battle ships the transAtlantic companies are not IdltS
Great strides are being made at Har
land Wolffs shipyards in Belfast in
tire construction of the two White Star
leviathans Olympic and Titanic which
are to surpass in tonnage and size the
Mauretania and her sister ship the Lusitania
The Olympic will be ready for launch
ing In August and the Titanic at the end
of next year The following are the
dimensions of each vessel compared with
other gigantic liners
Length
TonmzB in feet
OtjMpie 6000 0-
TUufe 6009 40-
MmtroUwbi 31933 ltd
LmtaMfe v 31I60 7C
Adriatic 4J5U J0-
9Iteitie c 236 m
But it is in the appointments of the new
vessels that the greatest interest centers
They are not to be built for speed but
for the comfort and convenience of
Five Thousand Passenger
There will bee greater deck and cabin
space Each ship will be able to carry
5000 persons and the crew of each will
number 600
The ships will be floating hotels
They are the first liners to afford their
patrons the luxuries of a swimming bath
sufficiently deep to permit of diving
Cabins aro to be constructed with private
shower and slipper baths
A commodious and wellappointed gymnasium is to give voyagers an opportu
nity for daily exercise while spacious
playrooms decorated with panels representing fairy tales and popular fables
will be provided for the children
Drawingrooms smokingrooms and a
library are to be at the disposal of the
voyagers One of the decks will be de
voted to an extensive ballroom and
should the fashion prevail a large skat
Ing rink will tys providedIn a sentence passengers may skate
dance smoke swim and dive and practice the arts of physical culture at their
willThere
are of course to be many din
ingrooms The principal one which is
to be elaborately decorated will seat no
fewer than 800 This is to be the most
commodious apartment on the ship</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045555/1910-02-04/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MONSTER LINERS
New TransAtlantic Boats to Carry
Five Thousand Persons
thousand tons rep
TWELVE the Increase In size
two mammoth liners
Olympic and Titanic nOW
being built by Messrs Harlllnd Wolff
Belfast for the White Star company
over the leviathan Cunarders Mauro
tanla and Lusltanla The tonnage or
each of these Is 33000 tons that of
each or the now White Star boats
is to bo 45000 tons and possibly
more Among the Belfast shipyard
workmen these great vessels have been
known for months past as the mystery
ships because ot the extraordinary
precautions which have been taken
to prevent their dimensions and de
sign becoming public property Some
thing however may now be said on
theso points
The new steamers will he completed about the end of next year and
will go on the SouthamptonNew York
service In the following spring They
will be by far the largest In the world und to equipment and decoration will he the finest on the water The now vessels will have A displacement or
GOOOO tons They are to ho about 940 feet long with a beam or 90 feet and tlto boat deck will bo more than 60 feet above the water Neither the Olympic nor the Titanic will bo highpower boats nor are their lines designed for great speed 21 knots being the average almod at as against the 25 of the Cunnrdors All immense amount of space which in fast boats is devoted to machinery will thus be saved for cabin accommo dation The carryIng capacity or the great boats will exceed that of any atloat today by Ilt least onethlrl1 Lack steamship will carry under nor mal conditions moro than jOOO per
sons all told
The crow will bo the largest ever employed on one merchant ship
more than GOO In all The monster
now liner will have nine steel decks The steamers are not only designed to eclipse everything else as yet
achIeved In passenger shipbuilding nq
regards the size but In their novelty
of equipment as well There will be a
large entrance hall a spacious din
ng room smolelngroom library
wornens parlor grill and lounging
rooms elaborately furnished to the last
One of the upper decks is to he completely Inclosel1 to serve as a ball
room or skating rInk By day this In
closure may be used ns a sun parlor
anti promenade It will he largo
enough to accommodate several hun dred passengers In planning the
cabins of the new liners the luxuries
of the most uptodllte hotels have been kept in sight and even improved upon These boats will offer not only extended suites of rooms but complete flats which will mako itt
possible to cross the Atlantic while enjoYing all the privacy or ones own
homo
The Olympic and Titanic will ho the first steamers to offer cabins with private baths attached In addition there will be a great swimming bath aboard both the Olympic and toe Titanic large enough to perntlt of
diving A gymnasium the largest and
most completely equipped afloatt 1111
be found on each of the new boats
The main dining saloon Which wIll
seat moro than GOO passengers will
be the largest single cabin on the ship
and In Its furnIshing and deco atlf11
the most Should a guest
tlro or this apartment In the week ho
Is at sea ho can wander from ono
cafe to another enjoYing practically
as much variety ns he might ashore
A veranda cafe will bo built on one
of the upper decks far astern looking
out over the sea and about fifty feat
above the water The decorations and general management will carry out the Idea of the openair cafes ot Southern
Eurore The cafe will be erected with
exposed rafters entwined with vines
and the sides will be latticed effects
to make the illusion of a cafe at the
seaside as complete as possible
Another novelty will be n Jrlll room
The cabin will suggest an old English
chop house with hlghbacled stalls of
ancient oak and broad low tables It
will be possible nt any hour of the day
or night for a passenger to use the grill room The palm garden will bo
still another refuge for those who
weary of the confines of the ship dur ing the lall5age
A garden will be located on the sun
deck and ht the winter months will bo
protected by a glass roof Hero will
bo found perhaps the most complete
illusion or the hotel ashore There will
be arbors artfully contrived to give the
effect of gardens covered with vines
and lowers The chlldlens room ot the
new liners wlll be the most sumptuous
apartment or Its kind ever attempted
The now liners will be as complete In
their safety devices as In their luxurious equipment Each boat will be di
vided Into upward or 30 steel compart
ments separated by heavy bulkheads
An automatic device on the bridge will
control all these heavy steel doors
making It possible for a single hand to
close them all In case ot danger Each
of these doors In turn will be electrically connected with a chart on the
bridge and wIn be represented by small
electric lights When one or these
doors closes the light will burn red The
officer on the bridge will thus be ahla
to see at a lance If all of the com
partments are closed Still another set
or safety devices will guard against
fire In every part of the ship
A combination of turbine and recIpro
cating engines will propel the vessels
It Is expected that a great economy
or coal will be effected by this ar
rangement The berths In Harland
Wolffs yards at Belfast In which
those wonderful ships are being built
are each 1000 feet long and capable of
bearing a dead weight of i5OOO tons
The Olympic is expected to be ready for
launching In the early autumn of 1910
London Dally News
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1910-07-11/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text> NEW LINERS
SOON 10 BE LAUNCHED
Hr Carlisle Says Olympic and
" Titanic Will Be Handsomest
Vessels Afloat.
LiOMSTER.S OF 45.000 TONS
tvrert Says There Is No Reason
'•'■■7 They Should Not. Be
x \ Ha-^ ec * — — Praise
fin Americans.
, Vs rt r VT — ah!*' "Alexander M Car
'~*r r*""e^2^ 'Tir'l— ' Of the big shipbuild-.
i ' : r-r -\\ Z '"-•" -• Harlassd & Wolff, at Belfast.
r%r^*£T.d probably the most • prominent
|g!Swj) constructor in Great Britain, ar-
T^an yesterday en the .Whit* Star
»T^> r, .-- ,-.-?• of the vessels "which grew
*F, *£ o^servatioti in the Belfast yards.
i-T^ •"s-i-t bssb Bf about sixty, and has
.**^i-v tie Crsa he represents for forty;
**^~~ezzs According c his friends he is
f: _.."- ■ talks little, but. thinks much.
s .rCl crpt-ired —1? yesterday when he
j^**^v £ V about the new-, theusand-fect
c t2.r eiants that are seen to leave
Kr^,;^ Vt Belfast
**".-: -vT~s -=thir.g at all to say." said Mr
fejjsie iSraptly. '"- tm not S" c — & to talk
S-TsSlps What "have" I com© over- for"
W--V2 SStle ?--- trip and the salt baths.
» *— rcirg right back en the Oceanic on
VfeSaai :
jri-ec - t-"- e £e2 - waase at Belfast was
J.. r -«t £5 coed se the salt water of the
r, J^ r of Vfeew York, Mr Carlisle replied :
■» s'-spese S&! But you see I came over to
«^> 2*iitt2s» -- - at sea: to get the sea air
%i tie salt t-stis or. board the Celtic"
Cr tie : "'" '-> tie bay -- Carlisle clung
v^c^v -- •£%' remark that he -would not
T ,v ajjsst ships, but he asksd many ques
.j.,., ibbct tie harbor and the cutters that
aX tie Celtic By degress v,«, warmed up
7. -_;* cibject o* stear^ship construction, to
•rt^zz. he hsi obßd his life, and declared
£2* -*- Clynplc and Titanic would but*
p^serSsenr ark -"--er- they cams here in
3£-
-- ..-tv, -»--rk or these big Etfiaisshlps is
rilTor. -.-:;-■ right and day," he "said,
— -j •?.«, "wd have the Olympic ready for
jssciis -— October Nothing can com
t--c with zs.ezz. in si;* and beauty You
rZI zit z. reflation. In rocm a^d decoratics
xtn. tbese -'cssels cc=s to >*e-v York."
BiiMd bet PsMio Wants.
-- yz- bs^evs ■- *-ii:<*iz.r BBC* iarjre
£-=silps-
-Te. I SJ:- -- reascr Thy great liners
£oulc zct be Mscstreeted if the travelling
jcil;c is Tilling tc pay for transpertaticn
■ ~ij?e they net aswSeSfiy lather hard to
—- -t-A »r v PT» retti — g — 1& pert?"
?':• v. _.. replied >Xr. Carlisle, with
••c r-■"■;'---"r -■"■;'---" of a. frown. '"With --i
*—c~j'^ -. rzzszes can s^'ir.^ £ big liner
jj-mrfl ""rtth ease. Quadruple screws are
zz rrzzztr advantage As long as you
izTr ewe big propellers 90s can hand:?- s
blr siip. '.' is net a a-uestior of the num
ber of prrpeilers. bat the depth they are
.- the waxes They must have solid water
w •'•ori In You know- - 1 =• cannot always
-_..- £i:ps as we would like to build
r-.err. We ia->-e tc b-uild the^n according to
*i£ depth cf the harbors they are re enter
I ■_-...-.: good •" ark has been done with the
■sr.:r:: Channel at ..this port. You
Ancri;ar:s are able people, and you can
"Ct--arythi^g yoa set your minds upon.- If
ysc wsat -.£ ships, are will build them
■•
'"T>o ywa believe in high speed like that
cf the Ururetar-ia -. - 1 the Losaftaals ' '
"That again is a Question for Che travel-
Utg pibSc If •'-..- people. "want to travel
fist they rinst expect to- pay for travelling
::_r. The Olympic and the Titanic will
zzve 2. sp^ed of ti ■cue knots That
is * rzzi iced for large ships. Ycu will
rse sc~e rc-sm -. those vessels The
rt^tfcrsoms -'-'111 be unusually large, ezsd
tier& will te as abundance of room every
■"•isre. Fir example, we win have an ex
c^zzzliy large room off the. dining Bar
tons T-ie-r* people may meet before din-
Sar .;: bold receptlcns. The decoration?
Till be unsurpassed They will ' be the
fr&sr tliit money can buy They will not
s^rc bs the most magnificent, bui they
Tin i« th& most substantial and solid that
«-ver -J-ere put tote a steamship."
If- Carlisle laughed when asked -what
isiarii cf the big Huropa. which the Hsm
lur?-American Lin© had contracted for
ti-rtly bifcirp- the recent financial panic in
' Tiev 2.r^ to have s. Sn?> new vessel,"* he
f-ii* Kf an exceptionally ' big typ* Hsrr
Alt&rt Eallin. of the Hamburg-Am«*rican
lise, is 'd. marvellous nan He know? the
Ft^cnsiir. business He has done big
"rlrps, ar.d vQ] continue to fin big things. ■
; -fe 'Z th© best, ■ad I understand one of
.*"*£ Tzzrt profitable and popular, BtaMneb*ns
"tf~The Hamburg-American L'r:"=- is the
-a-hich -i-ec. built several years
~€~> in cur yards st Belfast.
Ciyrrcic Launching in the Fa!!.
Aricfci when the Olympic and the Titanic
"•xeli visit tbea»«atan Mr C^rliEl* said.
'""*•'?- win launch The Olympic in October
tzi she should be in service in tbe middle
r ~ ISCi. The vessels are so large and there
t'j much to be done an them after the
hww^fag that they car.not be sent out be-;
f-.-* that time the Titanic will probably
ft ready MSI three or four months after
"-'^ Olympic sails on her maiden passage "
"*-'.i6 is the first vacation Mr Carlisle has
h;f in three years. The work at th*- yards
its kept him there constantly since his
rir!t here res years ap» He pointed to
t-.'j Brooklyn Bridge on the way -up bay
.--• remarked that he went across it on
<•-«•. . - th&. strands while it was in ceur?e
c! ccrstricticn. He expressed great Inter
'~' ;• the railroad terminal facilities in this
fcty, tnfl > stewed much praise on the < 3c
*«ssraLtton and ability of Americans He
f ; *Slss oat .IP Morgan as on* of -Assert-.
c - ? ?reir men, who invariably did that
"^iJcS hf. kd planned to do
"*'- rz'r* raofat than 7(*i,V<^ tons in ccurs*
*"- wtstructtoji at Belfaßt,*" he said, "and
*" .t Ere -r- unusually busy ICe one
-<■— lies ths great amount of work required
*'• bc!ld such big steamships 5? the
zr.i the Olympic. rbere '■ only
European
Visitors
• : npiran Columns
\i ' -York Tribune
a reliable £uidc to the best
Ebops, hotels and resorts.
Consult These Columns
Before Sailing
■ ' much valuable time will
be "saved for sightseeing.
sea ■"•a- (q r£t 6ve " 2 fairt rr3 « of it,
—^ that Is for one to visit the yards.
To. Be Things of Bsauty.
**** too. the average person cannot
understand the tremendous amount of
ac-sey put Into ta« decoration Only an
■TOM or an architect can know the real
fceautv or understand the time and the
money required to make the interior* of
the big ships. Thus far there- I? hardly
anything that caa surpass the decorations
OB the Mauritania Be patient and watch
few the decorations on the. Olympic."
air. Carlisle -was employed at the Eel
35- yards when the first Oceanic of the
hit* Star Line was launched. When the
second Oceanic, now in port, was launched
MS left the -ways under hi? direction.
The Olympic and Titanic -will be 4S<*V
ton vessels. They in called "thcusand
foof ships, but their length win be MO
fee* The new Hamburg: American liner
hot- under construction at Stettin will be
S?6 feet, -with a tonnage of 45. W. The
Msure-tar.ia. and the LuEitania are each "!*
feet in length . with a tonnage of 32.500
When it was announced last month in
London that the great docks -would be
constructed en the Mersey the Ctmard
L;?.!, it is said, planned to construct new
liters of 60.060 tons.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1911-05-31/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MONSTEB LINER LAUNCHED.
Steamer Titanic Slides Into Water
at Belfast.
BELFAST, May .11..Enthusiastic
crowds lined the banks of the River
l<agan and cheered lustily as the Whits
Star line s great steamer Titanic was
launched with appropriate ceremonies
this morning.
The Titanic will enter the White Star s
New York-Soutl^ampton service late in
the year, but her sister vessel Olympic
steams from . Southampton two weeks
hence for New York, and these two sea
monsters, each 45,000 tons register,
882Vt feet long and 92 H fo*t broad,
boast the distinction of being the
largest and finest, vessels in the world
These massive ships are also notable
for the enchanting beauty and the un¬
usual spaciousness of their passenger ac¬
commodations, and in first, second and
third class the greatest comfort is prom¬
ised. On both steamers swimming pools,
tennis and hand ball courts, and Turkish
and electric bath establishments ars
among the Innovations introduced for the
pleasure of the passengers.
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86086633/1912-04-03/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TITANIC'S MAIDEN TRIP.
Sister Ship to the Olympic of White
Star Line Snls Next Week.
Lorn! on, April The gigantic new
st Mam-shi- Titanic of thr White Star
line arrive.) todoy at Setithamptt n
from the MinN of her bulkiers at H-- lfast. She is to be marie re.iriy for herj
maitlen trip across the Atlantl , the
atnri al ertotch la scheduled for sVed.
Oaaday af next week. The Titanic is a
sister ship to the Olympic. 8he Is 0
leet hmg and has a d b placement of
r.o 000 tons. The travellmr Ust n the
bb ship will have coo names "Hi its
brt lass roll, in addition to 500 BOO
ot l lass and third cabin oa -
sengt ts. To this will be adder, the
n v oi sua makina a t ui tlo.tiiiK
pojsilatlon of mir1y t.ooe</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86058226/1912-04-10/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TITANTIC SAILS ON
HER FIRST VOYAGE
White Star Liner the Largest
Vessel that Ever Sailed
the Seas.
(National News Association)
LONDON, April 10. Carrying 1400
passengers the liner Titanic of the
White Star line, than which there is
no larger vessel afloat, sailed from
Southhampton today on her maiden
voyage bound for New York. The Tt-tan- ic
which is of 45,000 tons displacement Is sister ship to the Olympic.
All the special suites of rooms instituted as an innovation in the Titanic were occupied when the passage begun. These suites consist of bed
rooms, sitting room, bath room, and
servant's room and have their own
private deck promenade isolated from
the rest of the ship and not overlooked
by any other passengers.
The Titanic also possesses another
new feature in its Louis XVI. restaurant. Her sister ship the Olympic, also
has this feature but on a smaller
scale. It proved so popular, however,,
that the White Star company decided
to have Jhe one on the Titanic greatly
enlarged. Adjacent to it is a special
reception room for the use of passengers taking meals in the restaurant.
The Titanic while its engineering
principal is the same as that of the
Olympic, is expected by experts on
navigation to make faster time than
the Olympic because of a slight difference in the curvature of the propeller blades. </text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1912-02-26/ed-1/seq-12/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TITANIC, 45,000 TON MONSTER, READY FOR SERVICE
, here lying at the dock at Belfast,
preparatory to her trials, is bSZ
feet long and of 92 feet beam. She
is nearly 100 feet longer than any,
other ship in the world except her
sister, and her tonnage 15,000
is 13,00.0 in excess of that.jof the
biggest of rival liners.
Her engines 50,000 horsepower
are both turbine and reciprocal
. V '
Mj jmlI
Only the other day the "Lusi
tania" and the "Maurelania"
were the world wonder sisters of
the briny. Now they must yield
the palm to a new pair of marine
twins the Olympic and the Ti
tanic. This pair has just been fill
ed out by the completion of the
Titanic, the Olympic being al
ready in commission.
The Titanic, which is shown
ing, are expected practically to
eliminate vibration.
She has accommodations for
5,000 passengers.
She cost $7,500,000. I
The Titanic is not a spee'd mar
velshe makes but 2 knots as
against the Mauretania's 25
but she is the last word in the way
of comfort and luxury in trans
Atlantic travel.</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014546/1912-04-25/ed-1/seq-12/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85038615/1911-10-01/ed-1/seq-79/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WHITE STAR LINE TRANSATLANTIC SERVICES
NEW YORK.PLYMOUTH.CHERBOURG.SOUTHAMPTON
NEW YORK.QUEENSTOWN.LIVERPOOL BOSTON.QUEENSTOWN.LIVERPOOL NEW YORK.AZORES.MEDITERRANEAN.EGYPT BOSTON.AZORES.MEDITERRANEAN.EGYPT
The advent of Neptune's latest and greatest conqueror, the White Star Line's huge Triple-Screw Steamer "Olympic," marks an era of the greatest advancement in the ocean transportation of passengers. The surpassing dimensions of the "Olympic".exceeding those of any other ship.have made possible the utmost liberality in planning the passenger accommodations, which are upon a scale of greater magnificence than those of any other steamer.- Indeed, in comparison with this superb, crowning marine achieve¬ ment of the twentieth century the greatest buildings and memorials of the earth are dwarfed, and in the beauty and comfort of the appointments, combined with the White Star Line's unsurpassed cuisine and service, all the luxuries of the world's best hotels are more than equaled. -
as well
In
as
the
their
staterooms
vast area
every
and unusual
wish of the passenger has been anticipated and every "creature comfort" provided, while the public apartments, because of their engrossing beauty height, are exceptionally attractive.
The "Olympic's" sister vessel, "TITANIC".of similar dimensions and beauty.is now under construction at Belfast, and enters the line in March, 1912.
</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86086499/1910-09-30/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MORE OCEAN TITANS
Germany to Produce a New 50,-
COO-Ton Steamship.
The 45.000-Ton Liners of the White
Star Line, Now Being Built, to Be
Eclipsed—How the Struggle
Goes Forward.
Hamburg.—Much is heard today about the race for naval supremacy. But the race is no less keen in the
commercial contest and just now most
of the great steamship lines are pre- paring fresh giants for the ocean strug- gle Here again the rivalry is between the Germans and the Britsh, both being eager to hold the blue ribbon of
Atlantic transport, the chief shipping
route in all the world.
When the Lusitania and Mauretania relegated the German Deutschland to
a subordinate place as an ocean flyer the challenge was renewed, and today
on both sides of the North sea there Is
a strenuous endeavpr to create new
records in tonnage and speed. The
W hite Star line is well advanced with
the construction of two new monsters,
the Olympic and the Titanic, the Hamburg-American line answers with a
still bigger vessel, the Hansa. to the
great delight of the kaiser, and now
the C’unard line hints of plans
far beyond anything yet designed.
The Boston route must be considered first, because the latest ship to
take the water is the Franconia, anew
twr in-screw vessel of the Cunard fleet,
which will be the largest liner that
has ever entered Boston harbor. It is
just 70 years since the first Cunarder,
the Britania, opened up that route, and
though the Franconia is far below the
Mauretania in speed and tonnage, it
demonstrates well enough the shipping advance that has been made in
the span of a single human life.
For the Britannia was 207 feet long,
its tonnage was 1,154, speed eight and
\ t t | | \
y.-- . y
\ A \ 1.1 \_\
tc
1" 1
Showing the Evolution of Steamers.
l-’urst Bismarck, 1890-91: Deutschland.
1000; Kaiser Wilhelm 11., 1901; Mauretania,
1907, and the Hansa.
one-half knots an hour and the cabins
accommodated only 115 passengers
Now the Franconia's length is 625
feet, its gross tonnage 18,000 tonß,
displacement 25,000 tons; It can carry
2,600 passengers and its power is
twenty times as great as that of the
Britannia.
More than three thousand workmen
labored on the liner for 12 months up
to the launching at Wallsend-on-Tyne
The sister ship, the Laconia, has Just
been laid dowr n in the same shipyard
and will be launched next year. Next
in point of readiness are the White
Star liners, Titanic and Olympic, two
ocean giants under construction at
Belfast. Already they art immense
in bulk and when they are completed
they will be 45,000 tons each, or more
than 13,000 tons bigger than the Mau
retania. They are each 850 feet long
and it is understood they will be fitted
with turbine engines.
The Mersey dock and harbor board
has commenced the construction of a
huge new dock at Liverpool, but as it
will not he fully completed for three
years, it may be guessed that the pro
vision is mainly intended for the still
bigger Cunarder. that, report says
will run to 60,000 tons. Definite infor
mation is not forthcoming at the Cu
nard offices on this latest plan, but It
is not denied that the ifews that has
come from Germany of the new Ham
bnrg-American liner Hansa has roused
the Cunard directors to a determina
•ion to produce something that will
lick creation for some years to come
The big German liner Hansa’s ton
nage will be almost 50,000, or 18,00‘
more than the Mauretania and 5,00'
more than the Titanic. The Hansa
will not. according to present ar
counts, aim at'ocean speeding. It will
have turbine engines designed to run
it at 22 knots an hour, but the carg
and passenger accommodation will b*
immense. So carefully is It to be con
structed that it will not be in comrnis
sion before the beginning 1913.
Apart from the natural rivalry of
two great maritime nations in th<
American passenger and freight trade
•here is another influence on the Amer
lean side of the Atlantic that has made
for shipping developments. Since the
Armbose channel and other New York
narbor improvements were carried out
shipping men have found the limita
tions to the dimensions of their ves
sels removed. The biggest liners they
have ever dreamed of can now gain
ready access to New York, and the
difficulties at present He more in the
harbors of the old world than tin
new</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045293/1912-05-24/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WORLD’S LARGEST
SHIP MHED
HAMBURG, May 23. —The worlds
largest ship, the Hamburg-American
liner Imperator,, 10$ feet longer than
the ill-fated Titanic, today was launched
here by Emperor William, in the presence of the high officials of the government and a vast throng. The recent
loss of the White Star leviathan and
1,500 of her passengers gave rather a
sombre tone to today's ceremonies, but
nevertheless there was a ringing chorus
of cheers when the monster vessel slid
into the water. Among naval men
added interest was given to the launching because of the Titanic disaster and
the subsequent investigations in England and America, for it is claimed that
the Imperator now is the last word
in safety as well as in size. A conference of German maritime authorities
was held in Berlin a month ago when it
was decreed that the builders of the
new liner must sacrifice speed and
luxury to safety. They readily agreed.
The Titanic was 882 feet 6 inches
long. The Imperator is 893 feet long,
95 feet wide and 103 feet high. From
the captain's bridge to the water line
the distance is 81 feet. The topmost
of her 11 decks is as high as a five story
house. She will have a tonnage of
50,000 and accommodations for 5,000
passengers. There will be lifeboats
and life saving apparatus for every
person on board.
The Imperator is under subsidy of
the German navy and in time of war
can be pressed into transport service.
When the Titanic, Olympic, Lusitania
and Muretania were built, it was
rumored in diplomatic circles that
England boasted she could transport
an entire army to German territory
over night and immediately it was
announced that Germany would build
the biggest ship</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn92066979/1912-04-17/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1911-03-06/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88064469/1911-06-06/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The White Star line Titanic, sister
ship of the Olympic, was launched at
ielfast, Ireland. J. Pierpont Morgan
aind J. Bruce Ismay, the lntter of the
W hite Star line, witnessed the launchi g. The Titanic is of 45,000 tons
r gister, 182 1-2 feet long and 92 1-2
f1et beam</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn99021999/1910-03-20/ed-1/seq-9/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Ocean King is
a Native Son
of Old Ireland
Greatest Captain of the Shipping 'Industry, with Two Hundred Vessels at His Command.
DUBLIN, March 19. (Special to the Pub-Usher- 's
Press.) Ireland can now claim to
have the greatest shipping man In the
world. If any man ha tamed the coveted title of "Ocean King" It is Lord
Plerrle, who has. purchased the numerous
undertakings controlled by the late Sir
Alfred Jones, with whom he was associated
for many years. By this purchase Lord
Plerrle becomes by long odd th greatest
captain of the shipping industry. He is
not only the premier builder of giant ships,
but he has shown that he ha the genius
to operate as well as build. At present
the great firm of Harland ft Wolff, of
which he is the head. Is building for the
White Star line the Olympic and Titanic,
which will be the largest merchant steamer In the world. Lord Plerrle' Interest
In ocean steamship companies Is enormous,
but when he takes control of the two undertakings with which Sir Alfred Jones
was chiefly connected, namely, the Elder-Dempst- er
Shipping company, Limited, and
Elders ft Fyffes, he will acquire a great
measure of control over a combined fleet
of 245 ocean steamships owned by companies possessing a total capital of about
$150,000,000</text>
      </result>
	  <result>
	<id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82014086/1910-07-05/ed-1/seq-7/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>60,000-To- n Cunard tSeamships.
The greatest of the Cunard liners
now afloat have a gross tonnage of
32,500, while the White Star line has in the Titanic and Olympic vessels of
45.000 tons. Now the New York Times has a despatch from England saying that the Cunard company proposes to build two 60,000-to- n ships. Liverpool
is about to construct a dock suitable for liners 1,000 feet long as against
the 860-fo- ot length of the two White Star ships mentioned But New York has at present no means of taking
care of such huge hulks as the Cunard
company expects to put afloat. Springfield Republican.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
